In 1901, this ancient Greek artifact was discovered
in a shipwreck off the island of Antikythera.
3D X-ray scans have revealed
it contains 37 interlocking bronze gears,
allowing it to model the motions of the Sun and Moon
and predict eclipses decades in advance.
Constructed around 100 or 200 BC,
the Antikythera mechanism represents
a sophisticated early computer, the likes of which
would not be seen again for at least 1,000 years.
Now, of course, this computer didn't work
like modern digital computers.
It works by analogy.
The gears were constructed in such a way that the motions
of certain dials are analogous
to the motion of the Sun and Moon.
It is an analog computer.
Here is a simple analog computer
for adding two numbers together.
If you turn the black wheel some amount
and then turn this white wheel a different amount,
the gray wheel shows the sum of the two rotations.
In contrast, this is a digital mechanical computer
where you can add two single bit numbers.
So zero plus zero equals zero,
zero plus one equals one, and one plus one equals two.
These two devices illustrate the differences
between analog and digital computers.
Analog computers have a continuous range
of inputs and outputs,
whereas digital only works with discrete values.
With analog computers, the quantities of interest
are actually represented by something physical
like the amount a wheel has turned,
whereas digital computers work on symbols
like zeros and ones.
If the answer is, say, two, there is nothing in the computer
that is twice as much as a one.
In analog computers, there is.
For thousands of years, people used analog devices
like the Antikythera mechanism or slide rules
alongside digital devices like abacuses.
And up until the 1960s, the most powerful computers
on the planet were actually analog.
Digital computers exploded onto the scene
with the advent of solid state transistors,
and now almost everything is digital.
Most people have never even heard of analog computers,
but today that may all be changing.
Moore's Law, the idea that you can double the number
of transistors on a chip every two years,
it's reaching its limit because transistors
are nearly the same size as atoms.
Simultaneously, advancements in machine learning
are straining the capabilities of digital computers.
The solution to these challenges
may well be a new generation of analog computers.
(soft instrumental music)
One of the most important problems humans have faced
for millennia is predicting the tides.
Napoleon and his men nearly died crossing the Red Sea
due to a miscalculation of the rising tide,
and sailors routinely needed to know the tides
to bring their ships into port without running aground.
Most coastal locations on Earth
experience two high and two low tides per day,
but their exact timing varies as does their magnitude,
and this is partly caused by local factors
like the depth of the seabed and the shape of the shoreline.
In the late 1700s, to describe the tidal flow of the oceans
Pierre-Simon Laplace derived a set
of complicated differential equations.
They had no analytical solutions
so at the time they were basically useless,
but in the process of deriving his equations,
Laplace made a key finding.
Tides are driven at only
a few specific astronomical frequencies, including the Moon,
the Sun, and the eccentricity of the lunar orbit.
Each one of these factors contributes a sine wave
of a particular amplitude and phase to the total tide curve.
If someone could figure out
how to correctly combine these frequency components,
well, the tides could finally be predicted.
It took nearly a century, but in the 1860s,
William Thomson, later Lord Kelvin, took up the challenge.
Having completed several voyages
to lay the first transatlantic Telegraph cable,
he developed a fascination with the sea
and subsequently he threw his full scientific effort
into measuring and predicting the tides.
Tide gauges at the time used a buoy
to record the height of the sea onto a paper roll.
Kelvin set out to determine how sine waves
with the frequencies identified by Laplace
could add together to produce the observed tidal curve.
The key was to apply the work of French mathematician
Joseph Fourier who had shown how to decompose any function
into a sum of sine waves.
Most English scientists were skeptical of the work,
but Thomson was enthralled by it.
His first paper published at 17 was a defense of Fourier.
While it was straightforward to apply Fourier's analysis
to tidal curves, the computation required was enormous.
First, divide the tide curve up into short time intervals
and for each interval multiply the tide level
by a sine wave with the frequency of interest.
Add up the area of all these rectangles
and divide by the total time
and this gives you a single coefficient,
the amplitude of the sine wave with this frequency.
Then you have to repeat the process
for a cosine function with the same frequency.
Kelvin found that to make accurate predictions,
he actually needed 10 different frequency components
so that is a lot of multiplication and addition
to characterize the tides at just one location.
For each additional location,
you have to perform this analysis all over again.
And this is only half the problem.
Once you have the amplitudes and phases
of the sine functions, you have to add them up
to predict future tides.
Lord Kelvin spent years analyzing
and predicting tides by hand.
Then he had a stroke of inspiration.
Could you design a machine
to carry out these calculations automatically?
In Kelvin's words, to substitute brass for brains.
The resulting analog computers
were in use for nearly a century.
They even played a critical role
in the outcome of World War II.
Kelvin started with the problem of prediction.
Adding the sine waves together,
given you know their amplitudes and phases,
he knew he could create sinusoidal motion
with a device called a Scotch Yoke.
It extracts one dimension from uniform circular motion.
But to make a tide prediction,
he needed a way to combine 10 sine waves together.
He needed a mechanical analog for addition.
Stuck on this problem in 1872, Kelvin boarded a train
for a meeting with the main sponsor of his tidal research,
the British Association.
On the train, Kelvin bumped into a friend,
inventor Beauchamp Tower to whom he explained his dilemma.
Tower suggested he use Wheatstone's plan
of a chain passing round a number of pulleys.
And this was exactly the addition mechanism
Kelvin was looking for.
By attaching a pulley to each Scotch yoke
and running a weighted cord around them,
he could mechanically add
all of their contributions at once.
He scribbled down the entire plan
for this predictor machine by the end of the train ride.
He pitched it to the British Association
and secured funding to build it all before he returned home.
If you knew the relative contributions
of different frequency components,
Kelvin now had a machine to automate the tedious task
of predicting future tides.
This was a great leap forward.
Four hours of cranking the handle
yielded a full year of tidal predictions.
But for many years, the harder half of the problem
was still done by hand, breaking apart
an existing tide curve into its component frequencies.
To automate this step, Kelvin needed a machine
capable of multiplying the tide curve times a sine wave
and then taking its integral.
What would such a device even look like?
With his older brother, James Thomson,
Kelvin came up with a mechanical integrator.
It consists of a ball on a rotating disc.
Due to the rotation of the disc, the further the ball
is from the center, the faster it spins.
If the ball is at the very center of the disc.
It doesn't turn at all.
And if it's on the left side,
it turns in the opposite direction.
Now, the motion of the ball is converted into an output
via a roller, which moves a pen up or down
on the output graph paper.
So the way it works is you trace the function
you want to integrate with a stylus,
and the stylus controls the position
of the ball on the disc and hence its speed of rotation.
This is transferred through the roller to the output,
which plots the integral of the original function.
Now, to decompose a tide curve,
we don't just want to integrate the function.
We first want to multiply it by a sine wave
of a particular frequency, and the way to do this
is to make the disc rotate back and forth
at that specific frequency.
Now the rotation of the ball depends not only on where it is
on the disc, but also on how the disc
is turning at that instant.
You trace the tide curve with the stylus,
which moves the ball back and forth on the oscillating disc,
and the roller sums up the integral
of the tide curve times the sine wave.
Simply divide by the total time to get the coefficient.
Several of these ball and disc integrators can be connected
in parallel with each disc oscillating
at a different frequency to calculate the coefficients
for multiple frequency components at the same time,
Kelvin's analog computers
revolutionized our ability to predict tides.
Tidal curves from anywhere in the world could be turned
into a set of sinusoidal coefficients
using the ball and disc harmonic analyzer,
and the resulting sinusoids could be added together
to predict future tides
using his Scotch yoke pulley machine.
Kelvin's harmonic analyzers were the basis
for a landmark analog computer
called the differential analyzer,
and his tide predicting machines
were used well into the 1960s.
In fact, they were later overhauled
to include 26 frequency components
and used to plan the allied invasion on D-Day.
The Germans expected any invasion to come at high tide
to minimize the time Allied soldiers
would be exposed on the beaches
so they installed millions of obstacles
that would be underwater by mid tide,
many with explosive mines attached,
but the Allies spotted the obstacles and changed tack.
Instead they plan to begin the invasion at low tide.
This would allow demolition teams
to first clear channels through the obstacles.
Then the main forces
could come through those gaps as the water rose.
This would also give landing craft enough time
to depart without getting beached.
The low water times were different
at the five landing beaches by over an hour
so the invasion times were staggered
according to the tide predictions.
- This wasn't the only use
of analog computers in World War II.
Dive bomber aircraft would plummet out of the sky
directly toward their targets at up to an 80 degree angle,
and their rapid descents
made them very difficult to shoot down.
So the US began searching for devices
to automatically aim guns at dive bombers.
Most of the proposed solutions
fell into one of two categories.
Some were analog machines like Lord Kelvin's.
Others were essentially fast calculators.
Mechanical calculating machines like the abacus
had been around for millennia,
but they were far too slow to respond to dive bombers.
These new calculating machines sped things up
by using electrical pulses.
The committee considered naming these devices
after the pulses they used,
but member George Stibitz proposed a more general name,
digital because these machines operated
on numbers themselves or digits.
And this is the origin of the term digital computer,
but digital would have to wait.
Of all the proposals, an innovative analog machine
from David Parkinson went out.
At Bell Labs in New York,
Parkinson had been working on a device
to chart telephone data called an automatic level recorder.
It used a variable resistor called a potentiometer
to control the motion of a pen.
One night after hearing reports
of the harrowing Allied evacuation of Dunkirk,
Parkinson had a dream that he was on the front lines.
I found myself in a gun pit with an anti aircraft gun crew.
A gun there was firing occasionally,
and the impressive thing was
that every shot brought down an airplane.
After three or four shots one of the men in the crew
smiled at me and beckoned me to come closer to the gun.
When I drew near,
he pointed to the exposed end of the left trunnion.
Mounted there was the control potentiometer
of my level recorder.
When he woke up, Parkinson realized the device
he was building to control a pen
could be scaled up to control an anti-aircraft gun.
- He shared this idea with his supervisor
and after receiving approval from the military,
they set out to make Parkinson's dream a reality.
Researchers at Bell Labs had recently invented
an analog electrical device
called an operational amplifier or op-amp.
It could perform mathematical operations with voltages,
like addition and multiplication.
They used these op-amps to create an analog computer
that could solve the ballistics equations
for anti-aircraft guns.
Using radar and optical sights to obtain the speed, altitude
and direction of enemy planes,
the M9 Gun Director, as the computer was called,
could rapidly calculate
the correct trajectory and fuse setting.
Potentiometers were used
to ascertain the direction the gun was pointing.
This was not the first electric analog computer,
but it was an important one.
In World War I, it took an average of 17,000 rounds
to take down a single airplane.
In 1943, after the invention of the M9,
it took an average of only 90.
During the war, the US invested big in analog computers.
If you break down their total military budget,
the third largest single expense was the development
and production of an incredibly complex
mechanical analog computer called The Norden Bombsight.
Unfortunately, they didn't get their money's worth.
Designed by the eccentric Dutch engineer Carl Norden,
the Norden Bombsight was built
to enable high-precision airborne bombing.
It implemented 64 different simultaneous algorithms,
including one that compensated
for the rotation of the Earth as the bomb fell.
(explosion resounds) The Norden was one
of the most closely guarded secrets of the war.
To prevent the technology from falling into enemy hands,
American bombardiers carried handguns
specifically to destroy it in the event of a crash.
But despite its hype and funding,
the Norden didn't work as advertised.
With over 2,000 fine parts,
it required extreme precision to manufacture.
The problem with analog computers
is that the physical device is a model for the real world.
So any inaccuracy in the components
translates into inaccuracy of the computation.
And since there will always be some slop
in the connections between parts,
if you run the same calculation twice,
you won't get the exact same answer.
In the American campaign against Japan,
bomber crews using the Bombsight were unable
to destroy critical Japanese war infrastructure,
and ultimately the US abandoned
its precision bombing approach
and instead blanketed whole Japanese cities in napalm.
As the war progressed, digital computers gained traction.
The digital and electronic Colossus machines
of Bletchley Park in the UK
were critical to breaking German codes.
In the United States, the military invested
in an enormously complex
and expensive digital machine known as ENIAC.
It was designed to speed up the calculation
of land artillery firing tables.
At the time, these were computed
using differential analyzers,
the analog mechanical computers
based on Kelvin's harmonic analyzer.
Although not finished until after the war,
ENIAC demonstrated the power of digital computers.
It's considered by many to be the first modern computer.
What really opened the door to this digital revolution
was the discovery made by Claude Shannon
in his 1936 Master's thesis.
He showed that any numerical operation can be carried out
using the basic building blocks of Boolean algebra.
Two values, true or false, also notated as one or zero,
and three operations, and, or, and not.
This makes digital computers
the ideal versatile computing machines.
In contrast, each analog computer
is an analog for only one type of problem.
Furthermore, since digital computers
operate on ones and zeros,
they're more resilient in the face of noise.
It would take a large error to mistake a one for a zero
or vice versa, whereas even small errors in analog computers
can grow and ultimately swamp the signal.
So these days, everything is digital.
Our phones, computers, and internet data centers,
even TV and radio is now being broadcast as digital.
And the advantages are obvious.
Since digital devices operate on symbols,
usually zeros and ones, they provide exact answers
and repeat the calculation and you get the same result.
They are robust to noise.
Plus since only a few components
are required to perform virtually any computation,
those components have been miniaturized and optimized,
making digital computers
the ideal universal computing machines.
So you would think analog computers would be long gone,
a relic of the distant past,
but analog may now be making a comeback.
There are startups actively working on analog computers.
Why is this happening? What could be the benefit of analog?
I wanted to put all of this into one video,
but the story is too good to bury 20 minutes in
so that is coming up in part two.
Be sure you're subscribed to the channel
to be notified when that comes out.
(radio tuning chirping)
I'll give you a hint about the sequel
in this section of the video,
which is sponsored by brilliant.
Brilliant is a website and app that uses interactivity
to help you learn STEM concepts.
For the sequel to this video, it would be a good idea
to brush up on artificial intelligence, which you can do
with Brilliant's courses on neural networks.
Here, you can analyze
how a neural network decodes your handwriting.
I also recommend their calculus courses,
which are highly interactive.
What's great about Brilliant
is how it gets you to step through topics,
answering questions as you go.
And that way you can't trick yourself into thinking
you already understand everything because you're constantly
putting your knowledge to the test.
Personally, I find their courses challenging,
which they should be in order for you to learn anything.
But if you ever get stuck,
there's always a helpful hint close at hand
and more in-depth explanations
are available if you want them.
As the holiday season is upon us,
an annual subscription to Brilliant makes an awesome gift
for any curious learners in your life.
And whether it's for you or someone else,
Brilliant is offering 20% off an annual subscription
to the first 200 people to sign up.
Just go to brilliant.org/veritasium.
I'll put that link down in the description.
So I want to thank Brilliant for supporting Veritasium,
and I want to thank you for watching.