- This is the world's largest 3D metal printer.
这是世界上做大的3D打印机
It was built by Relativity Space,
由Relativity Space公司打造
a startup that aims to print an entire rocket,
这家初创公司的目标是
including fuel tanks and rocket engines, in just 60 days.
在60天内，打印一支包括了燃料仓和发动机的火箭
I'm like looking inside a 3D printed rocket
我面前的就是一支3D打印的火箭
that is actually gonna go to space.
而且它真的能飞上太空
This giant hunk of metal, it's unbelievable.
这么一大块金属，真是难以置信
This video is sponsored by Omaze.
本视频由Omaze赞助
Offering you the chance to win a trip to space.
他能提供一个让你赢得太空之旅的机会
More about that at the end of the show.
详情请见视频结尾
- There's a lot of UV coming off the welds,
焊接点会有很强的紫外线
you can film it, but don't look directly at it.
拍摄没问题，但是不要用眼睛直接看
You get sunburned fast,
强紫外线会让人很快晒伤，
so it's like you're suiting up to go in a volcano.
所以我们全副武装，按照进火山的标准来
All right, we're gonna go in to the 3D printer,
好了，我们现在能进去看看
and see how it works.
3D打印机是怎么工作的
All right, so, yep, just hold this up.
好啦，可以，拿着这个
Don't look at it.
别直接看
We are in the printer.
我们进入了这里
- I can see it over there.
能看到打印机就在前面
- If we walk around here, we can get up close.
走这边能看得近一点
(machinery whirring)
(machinery beating)
So that's the wire melt team,
这个就是线材融化模组
and the print head moving around.
打印头在不断移动
So that's the plasma discharge, and it's hard to tell,
等离子体在放电，我不确定具体时长
but it's doing things every couple of milliseconds,
大约几毫秒放点一次
it's actually changing the electric wave form,
通过不断改变放电的波形
which is how it's controlling the deposition so well.
来来控制金属的精确沉积
- Do you know the temperature of it?
你知道这里的温度么？
Like, is it just above melt temp?
比方说，温度刚刚超过了熔点？
- It's just above melting for aluminum.
是的，比铝的熔点高一些
Yeah, probably a few hundred degrees above.
大概几百度吧
- The melting point of aluminum is 660 degrees Celsius.
铝的熔点约为660摄氏度
So the whole body of the rocket
所以，整个火箭的身体
is effectively melted together one tiny bit at a time.
都是一点点融化再凝固得来的
- All the raw metal
火箭所需所有的原材料就是这个
for the whole rocket that's printed is this.
It's a, you know, we kind of joke
我们都开玩笑
it's like Charlotte's web.
这就是“夏洛特的网”
Like a spider silk, but this is an aluminum alloy
就行蜘蛛丝一样，但这里是铝合金丝
that's on a wire spool.
绕线盘上都是
We actually print about 10 inches a second.
打印速度大约每秒10英寸（每秒25厘米）
So this wire is really going super fast,
这个线跑得飞快
and then the combination of lasers and plasma arc discharge
然后激光和等离子体放电共同作用
are working to melt both of them together at the same time.
把铝合金丝融化
- So where does the wire come out?
铝丝从哪儿出来？
- So it's right there, and then the electric arc discharge
这里，然后电弧在尖端处放电
happens right at the tip of the wire too.
- This is a camera.
- Yeah, that's a camera.
这是摄像头？对
- But why would you want to 3D print a rocket?
但是，为什么我们要3D打印火箭呢？
Is it just because we can?
就因为我们有这个能力？
It's funny to me that
听起来这很有趣
you had this experience with 3D printing where you're like,
你有3D打印的经验
oh, 3D printing is clearly the future.
然后说，啊，3D打印可是未来科技啊
Whereas, I feel like a lot of people's experience
然而，很多人和我一样，用3D打印的体验
with 3D printers as mine has been,
it's like incredibly frustrating.
都惨不忍睹
I feel like 3D printing is that thing
我感觉3D打印就是那种看起来不错
that seems like it should be great,
and yet whenever I try it,
一上手亲自做，总是得不到满意的效果
I don't get a result that I'm happy with.
- Yeah, I know.
是，我明白
I can tell you, we had plenty of experiences
我想说的是，在头几年，我们有很多（失败）的经验
the first couple of years,
where we ended up with a pile of metal and it didn't work.
打印出来一大堆东西，结果根本不能用
- But there are actually good reasons to 3D print a rocket.
不过用3D打印技术来生产火箭还是有很充足理由
A rocket has four major systems.
火箭由四个主要系统构成
Payload, guidance, structural, and propulsion.
载荷、制导、结构、推进
The bulk of the rocket is made up of the propulsion system,
火箭很大一部分都是推进系统
including the propellant tanks and the rocket engines.
包括了燃料仓和火箭发动机
Cryogenic fuel and oxidizer are pumped
燃料和助燃剂由燃料泵喷入燃烧室内
through an injector into the combustion chamber
where they react, releasing an enormous amount of heat.
反应燃烧后产生大量的热
This causes the exhaust gases to expand,
使得排出的气体迅速膨胀
exiting the rocket nozzle at high velocity.
以极高的速度排出发动机喷嘴
The faster this exit velocity
出口速度越快
and the higher the mass flow rate,
喷出工质的速率越高
the more thrust that can be generated.
火箭发动机产生的推力就越大
So rockets are huge, complex engineering projects,
因此，火箭是一项极为庞大，极为复杂的工程项目
which up to this point have largely been manufactured
同时，现阶段还是通过传统的手段来建造的
using traditional techniques.
That means before you can build the rocket,
也就是说，要想造一支火箭
you first have to build the
tools to build the rocket.
For example, to build
NASA's next huge rocket,
the Space Launch System or SLS,
they first needed to construct
the vertical assembly center or VAC.
This is a 170 foot tall
tool for welding together
the domes, rings, and barrel sections
of the rocket's fuel tanks.
- They built that like an aerospace thing,
and they've had to spin up all
these custom tooling designs
and validate that those work
before actually starts
building the rocket.
And they finally got one
being assembled on the pad
after 11 years of development.
In contrast, Relativity Space the company,
is just five and a half years old,
and they plan to launch
their first rocket this year.
- I see this as a like
old engineering style
versus Silicon valley
style of build something,
figure out what's wrong with it,
and build another thing
that fixes those, right?
The differences, I've always
done that with software.
These guys are doing it
with aerospace hardware.
- So this is the actual
rocket tank structure
of what we're gonna be launching to orbit
at the end of this year.
So this actual thing
is launching to space.
- That will go to space?
- This will go to space,
and it's by far the largest
3D printed product really,
of any type ever made that's gonna fly.
I think maybe of any type in the world.
- But it still looks 3D printed.
Like you can still see the layers.
- Yeah, yeah, you can
still see the layers.
It only adds an extra
5 to 10% of the mass
with the roughness.
When you actually cross
section the material
and look at the machine parts of it,
it looks like normal metal.
Like actually at this end,
this is printed as well.
We just machine it afterwards.
So it looks like normal
metal in the joint sections.
- Does the surface roughness
cause any aerodynamic problems?
- No, none at all.
Yeah, it's actually the
exact same aerodynamically.
This whole thing, we simulate
the print before printing,
because if you just printed,
you know, the 3D file
and said press print, you
would end up with a printer
that's warped and like material
falling all over the place
that wouldn't actually work.
So we've invented software
that reverse warps
the whole part before printing it.
So the robots are actually doing this
really wobbly, weird shape,
but then it's actually perfectly straight
within a human hair at the entire length.
- As it cools
- As it cools.
The warpy thing turns into the...
- And then we simulate all of that.
So it's a big computational solver
that simulates it, and there's
many, many other problems
we've had to solve to actually get
printing a rocket to work.
But it's all these little pieces
over the last couple of years,
and we've really started
to hit some breakthroughs,
which is also why now
you see a whole rocket.
Yeah, you can step up here actually
if you want.
- Can I?
- Yeah, yeah.
(man laughs)
- Hello.
I'm like looking inside
a 3D printed rocket
that is actually gonna go to space.
- Yes.
- This giant hunk of metal.
It's unbelievable.
There's like rings inside.
- Those are printed in stiffeners.
And so those help prevent the rocket
from buckling and crumpling.
So if you had a Coke can,
and didn't pop the tab,
if you try to step on it,
it's almost impossible
because there's pressure inside
that keeps it from buckling.
But then when you pop the tab,
there's no pressure and you
can crunch it super easy.
It's not hard at all.
So rockets are the same.
The 50 PSI of pressure,
which is about the same as a car tire,
keeps it inflated and
keeps it from crumpling,
but then the stiffeners
also help keep it rigid.
- Yeah, so believe it or not,
a rocket tank is thinner
versus its diameter
than a Coke can.
So when you look at a Coke can,
you know how big it is
and then how thin it is,
a rocket tank is actually
thinner than that.
So yeah, it's pretty light.
It has to be very light.
- Sure.
Aerospace companies started
using metal 3D printing
over a decade ago to
construct small complex parts.
For example, the injector.
- That is the most important
part of any rocket engine,
where you basically gotta
take the liquid propellant,
and turn it into a fine mist
that mixes really rapidly.
And those have actually been transitioned
to 3D printing all over the industry.
- Traditionally, something like this,
it's a bucket engine injector.
So it mixes liquid oxygen
and liquid methane propellants together,
and this is what actually
produces all the fire and flame
that is in a rocket engine.
Traditionally, it would be over
a thousand individual pieces
and it would take nine months,
but here we're 3D printing
the whole thing in one piece.
It takes two weeks and
it costs 10 times less.
- One of the big benefits of 3D printing
is reducing the number of parts.
Have you ever thought about
how inside a rockets combustion
chamber, it gets really hot.
Up to 3,500 Kelvin.
That's hot enough to
melt virtually any metal.
So how do the combustion chamber
and rocket nozzle not melt?
The answer is they're cooled by passing
the cryogenic propellants over them.
- On the Space Shuttle main engines.
I love to talk about them
because inside those engines,
it's hot enough to boil iron.
On the outside, you can freeze stuff
to the exterior of this
because you're running liquid
hydrogen through these things.
But to make those,
you basically had to take
thousands of very small pipes,
and then you would form them
into the shape of the combustion
chamber and the nozzle,
and then you would braze
weld them together.
And this was a ridiculously
labor-intensive task.
You would have 1,080 individual
pipes running up the side,
all having to be weld together
to make the combustion
chamber and the nozzle
on the Space Shuttle engines.
So you can actually 3D print these things.
- This is a rocket
nozzle being 3D printed,
and you can see the channels
for the cryogenic propellants
being printed right into the single part
instead of having to add a
thousand pipes on the outside.
Smaller parts like these
are typically 3D printed
using metal powder and lasers.
- So you can see the cooling channels
are all being built as the one piece.
So this is a nozzle.
It really just lays down a layer of powder
that's about a 20th the
thickness of a human hair.
So it's really, really fine layers
just over and over and
over and over relentlessly
for probably about a week or so,
and then out comes the rocket nozzle
all printed as one piece.
It's way cheaper than traditional.
And this has four lasers going at once.
- That's amazing.
- I get asked a lot, well,
aren't 3D printed metals
not very strong?
Or how can it actually work?
But the printed materials are stronger
than they would be built
traditionally, actually.
It's counterintuitive.
- It is.
- Because we develop our
own custom alloys in house.
So we have a whole material science team
just developing our own
alloys for 3D printing,
and the fact that it melts
and then cools and solidifies
very, very quickly, you can take advantage
of that physics principle
to get really strong alloys.
- Another major benefit of 3D printing
is that it allows for rapid iteration.
You can build a part quickly, test it,
and then redesign rapidly and print again.
- So this is a version of the engine
that's about three
years old at this point,
but what's amazing is
when you actually look
at the engine design today,
it looks entirely different than this.
So each version we build, we
can iterate and make better.
So that's the other, you know,
when we say software driven manufacturing,
that's really what it is.
Since you don't have fixed tooling,
all the part geometries
are just controlled
via the CAD model, and then
the printers just print
direct from file essentially.
It means you can actually change
the design extremely fast.
So building a whole engine
only takes us about a month.
So then a month later, you
can do a better version,
and a month later, a
better version than that.
So this particular one will actually be,
I believe one of the first flight engines
that's actually launching to
orbit on our first rocket.
- So this tubing, not 3D printed, right?
- Not today.
- Okay.
- In the future versions,
we're actually integrating that
into the printed housings.
And we're gonna have a way
that that's all printed too.
- Perhaps the biggest impact
of the 3D printing approach
could be to totally transform
what a rocket looks like.
With 3D printing,
engineers can build parts
that would be impractical or impossible
with traditional techniques.
Smooth, curvy, bio-inspired designs
are just as easy to print
as ordinary structures.
- This is actually part of
our next rocket, Terran R.
So it's even larger.
- This is like the base of a tank.
- Yeah. Yeah.
So it's gonna go out.
It's almost done printing.
It's gonna go out about to here.
So it's 16 foot diameter,
but it's almost like a shell.
- I was gonna say like,
this reminds me of suddenly
we're in The Little Mermaid or something.
- Yeah, yeah.
Yeah, it's just for stiffness though.
- It's not that you plan
to make it bio inspired.
It's like that structure is
actually the optimal structure.
- Yeah, yeah.
- We're actually designing
many features in the rocket
that could not be manufactured
unless it was 3D printed,
which is one of the secret sauces
of why you had to build a
whole company around it,
is because our rocket actually looks
entirely different 3D printed
than it does traditionally.
Like in my mind, it's been more akin
to like gas internal
combustion engine to electric.
You know, really, people
are trying to put batteries
and electric motors into
existing products for decades.
Like everyone knew electric
vehicles were the future,
but Nissan and Ford had
really not compelling products
for a long time.
It wasn't until a company
came along called Tesla
that decided, well, actually
the shift to electrification
means the batteries, the
electric motors, the factory,
the design of the product,
how we're actually
gonna scale the company,
the supply chain, all of it's different
because of electrification.
I mean, that's in some ways,
the dirty secret of electric cars
and why they're able to
be automated in production
because the part count is so much lower.
So for a fully 3D printed rocket,
we have a hundred times fewer parts,
which is what we're guiding to.
There's no fixed tooling
in our factory at all.
Unlike the rest of aerospace
that's still really, 60 years later,
even since Apollo building products
one at a time by hand
with hundreds of thousands
to millions of individual parts.
And no one's really changed that paradigm
of how an aerospace factory
actually fundamentally works.
- Yeah, this is the new
fully 3D printed rocket.
So yeah, we'll have dragon
fly wing type structures
and we're building it so.
But that's the first one,
and then that's that one for scale.
So yeah, it is definitely bigger.
Yeah, so our rocket is named
Terran One and Terran R,
and then our 3D printer's Stargate.
So all the things here at Relativity
are named after StarCraft.
So yeah, of course, the Stargate printer
was with the Protoss
used to warp in spaceships.
And so, that's what's warping
in spaceships at Relativity.
We have a system in our
avionics called the Pylon
that we have to build a lot of.
So we always joke, we have to
construct additional Pylons.
Most people don't know how rockets
are built traditionally at all anyway.
And I think a lot of
people assume it's rockets,
so shouldn't it be already very advanced
and robots everywhere and you know,
Elon's got Space X and Tesla,
so doesn't Space X just look like Tesla
with all these robots and automation?
But that's really not true.
I mean, aerospace hasn't
adopted automation at all.
- One of the issues, right,
is that you're not making
a lot of rockets?
- Right?
- So there's no incentive
to like figure out
how to tool up a factory
to like pump out rockets
like a hundred a day or something.
- Exactly.
- Like you would for cars.
- Exactly, you're not making a lot.
Even with commercial aircraft,
you're not making nearly as many
and there's orders of magnitude
more parts and complexity.
A commercial aircraft has
several million individual parts.
So to have robots assemble
several million parts
when an automobile has tens of thousands
is completely different.
It's a much harder problem.
So that's where 3D printing
is automation for aerospace
because you're not assembling
all those parts with robots
like you would with a car,
you're assembling them in the 3D file
and then the printer just
prints them assembled.
- The plan for Relativity Space,
is it low-earth orbit or is
it going further than that?
- So for Terran One, it's
mostly low earth orbit.
The first rocket.
Terran R can actually send
payload to the moon to Mars.
I mean, it's pretty, pretty huge.
I founded the company
because I really thought
that there needed to be, you know,
dozens of hundreds of
companies making Mars happen.
We're focused on taking
this 3D printing tech
and what we call the
factory of the future,
and one day shrinking it down to something
we'll actually launch to Mars
and build an industrial base.
So that's the long-term
vision of the company,
is build the industrial base on Mars.
In many ways, this factory
is just a prototype.
It's still far smaller
than a traditional factory.
It's far lighter.
And I think it's inevitable
someone has to build this company.
- I don't know that in 10, 20 years
that you will be 3D printing
rockets all the time.
Because if you are flying lots of rockets,
it becomes cheaper to have
a dedicated machine for it.
I do think that as a
company, they are well-placed
because even if Terran fails
to capitalize on the market,
even if nobody wants to
use it as a launch vehicle,
they are clearly now the world experts
on 3D printing rocket hardware,
'cause they've done everything, right?
They've tried to apply
3D printing to places
where a lot of people dismissed it.
So I think they're sort
of secure as a company.
Whether we will see rockets
being 3D printed all the time?
That's a good question.
- There've been a lot of talk recently
about billionaires going to space.
- Yeah.
- Will a 3D printed
rocket make it possible
and a lot cheaper for me to go to space?
- Yes, I mean, certainly what we're doing
is lowering the cost.
So our rockets are
costing about five times
to, you know, I believe we can get to 10
or even a hundred times cheaper
with a fully reusable rocket
than what we have today.
So it can definitely
climb down the cost curve.
But I also think, you know, going to Mars
and the first people that are going,
it really is about what is the
point of being a human being?
Like for me, why go to Mars?
If we were having this conversation
and a million people were
living on another planet,
I think it would expand the possibilities
of human experience and what
it means to be a person.
Like we'd have YouTube channels on Mars
and people sharing what life
on Mars is like versus earth.
And there'd be long distance
Amelie, like love stories.
Like I think there's
just a lot of richness
in what human culture
and society can be about.
Yes, I think there's criticism about,
you know, billionaires going to space
and I don't agree with.
You know, all of the projects
need to actually add up to
some vision that is meaningful.
I think that's really important.
But I do think going to
Mars is really just about,
you know, we've lived
for generations on earth,
so what's it all about like,
why do we want to keep
improving and getting better
and furthering society on earth?
So for me, it's pretty existential.
What it means to be a human being.
(techy sound effect)
- Hey, this video is sponsored by Omaze.
Offering you the chance
to win a trip to space.
The winner will get two seats
on one of Virgin Galactic's
first commercial space flights.
Meaning you and a guest
will travel 80 kilometers
up in the sky.
You'll get to see the
curve of planet earth,
experience weightlessness,
and become one of the
few people in the world
to have gone to space.
And you also get to
join Sir Richard Branson
for a personal VIP tour
of Spaceport America.
The flight is estimated to
take place in early 2022.
So enter at omaze.com/veritasium
for your chance to win.
Now, Omaze partners with charities,
in this case Space for Humanity,
an organization whose mission
is to expand access to space
and train global leaders
in the eventual goal
of creating a sustainable future.
So part of your contribution
supports this cause.
To potentially win a trip to space
and support Space for
Humanity, a great cause,
go to omaze.com/veritasium.
I will put that link
down in the description.
So I wanna thank Omaze
for sponsoring this video,
and I wanna thank you for watching.