In 2014, the qualifying exam for the US Physics Team had this as question 19:
A helicopter is flying horizontally at constant speed.
A perfectly flexible uniform cable is suspended beneath the helicopter.
Air friction on the cable is not negligible.
So, which of the following diagrams best shows the shape of the cable
as the helicopter flies through the air to the right?
Is it A. hanging straight down.
B, hanging diagonally to the left?
C, this hook shape.
D, the inverted hook shape,
or E, a kind of S bend.
Now , apparently there 's been a certain amount of controversy
about the correct answer to this question.
So, today we're gonna go up in this helicopter,
and put this question to rest once and for all.
Let's go.
A portion of this video was sponsored by SimpliSafe, which allowed us to rent this helicopter.
More about them at the end of the show.
I've got several thousand hours of carrying sling loads,
fire buckets,
concrete buckets , doing power line construction, actual power poles.
You name it, anything that needs to be moved around the mountains,
I 've done .
Biggest concern that I have is that the rope's gonna interact with the rotor wash
as its interaction with the ambient air around the aircraft.
And we'll get a whipping action that falls down the rope
and flips around on the end.
To a point that we worry if it will have a tendency
to work its way back up towards the aircraft.
Obviously, we don't want it getting in the rotors
or the tail rotor.
- [Derek] Alright, we're all set.
Movin' up.
Here I'm deploying a battle rope, like you'd see at the gym.
This one is about 15 meters long
and it weighs 20 kilograms .
- [Craig] See, the whipping action's begun.
- [Derek] I see it.
So, if we go really slow, will we avoid that?
- We 'll see.
We'll see where the rotor wash stops interacting with the rope
and the ambient wind.
Now the setup looks pretty simple, but few people agree on what the right answer should be.
题目条件看似非常简单 但关于正确答案人们却莫衷一是
When I polled YouTube,
我在 YouTube 上发布投票的时候
the most common answer was C.
最常见的选项是 C
Well done on making that beautiful bell curve by the way.
顺便一提 这条钟型曲线画得漂亮
We got in touch with the question's author,
我们和问题的提出者 Paul Stanley 教授
Professor Paul Stanley.
取得了联系
There was some creative students who actually constructed
有些异想天开的学生其实构想了
their own homemade scenarios.
他们自己的情境
One had a fan to the side
侧面有一个旋翼
and another fan blowing downward
另一个螺旋桨则往下吹
so that they could mimic the motion of the helicopter
这样他们就能模拟直升机的运动
and suspended a string and said, "Oh, it's this design."
然后在上面悬挂一条绳子 他们说 哦 就是这种设计
And the faculty members looked at it and said,
我们的教授看到之后说
" Oh , obviously I can prove that the answer is this answer."
哦 我能证明显然这个就是正确答案
They just didn't agree with each other.
但他们之间的意见却不能统一
- If we approximated as a chain of rigid links
- 如果我们把它近似看作一串互相链接的刚体
- I don't think you can just do that.
- 我不觉得你能那么做
- What do you think?
- 你的意见如何
- I think you're more likely to be C.
- 我觉得答案更像是 C
- I think it is D. - D?
- 我觉得是 D - D
- My guess is B.
- 我猜是 B
- What do you think? - B. - B?
- 你觉得呢 - B - B
- Imma go with A.
- 我支持 A
- Interestingly, no one chose E.
- 有趣的是 没人选择 E
Have you locked in your prediction?
你锁定你的选项了吗
To make sure the rope doesn't come up into the rotors of the helicopter,
为了保证绳子不被卷进直升机的螺旋桨
pilot Craig wanted to keep the rope on our right side
飞行员 Craig 希望让我们把绳子放在右侧
so he could keep an eye on it.
这样他可以留意到
Looks pretty good.
看起来不错
- I'm trying to make it look good.
- 我正在试着让它保持稳定
I mean I'm really working on it.
我的意思是我正在做这件事
- You're working hard.
- 幸苦你了
So, we're not going straight forward.
所以 我们不会向正前方飞行
We're actually going diagonally forward and to the left.
实际上我们在往左前方运动
But you can clearly see the rope is hanging straight,
但是你能明显看到悬挂的绳子
diagonally to the left.
呈一条斜线偏向左边
That's a pretty good diagonal, man.
这条斜线基本没有弯曲
So, the correct answer to the question is B.
所以 正确答案是 B
You wanna pull it in?
- Up it comes.
- [Derek] We're going to try a few more experiments,
adding a weight to the end of the rope and then a parachute.
But first I want to discuss why the answer is B.
There are two external forces acting on the rope,
gravity pulling it down and air resistance to the left.
When flying along at constant speed, these forces must be perfectly balanced
by the tension in the rope.
Now, when I set out to do this experiment,
I wondered if the rope would be affected by the air pushed down by the helicopters rotor,
but judging by our results.
This was not the case.
- The rotor wash doesn't extend down below the helicopter,
all that far. It dissipates pretty quickly.
- So, you can consider the air resistance on the rope as entirely due to its motion through still air.
Imagine dividing the rope up into many short sections.
Each section has the same weight and experiences the same amount of air resistance
because it has the same cross-sectional area.
And it's moving at the same speed.
Now, the tension in any section of the rope
must balance the sum of the air resistance
and weight of all the sections beneath it.
So, the tension is zero at the bottom of the rope,
and it increases linearly up to a maximum at the top.
You can see the tension is small at the bottom of the rope, and that's why it wiggles around
while the top is much steadier.
Now, although the magnitude of tension changes
throughout the rope, it's direction doesn't.
And that's because the ratio of air resistance
to weight is the same at every point along the rope.
That is why a uniform flexible cable hangs in a straight diagonal line
when pulled at constant speed by a helicopter.
If the helicopter flies faster,
the angle of the rope changes, but it still makes a diagonal straight line
because the ratio of air resistance to weight
is still constant along the entire length of the rope.
But this got me wondering, "What would happen if we added a weight
to the end of the rope?"
Here, I have a 20 pound, that's an eight or nine kilos kettlebell.
And I want to ask you to make a prediction.
What shape do you think the rope will make now?
Will it still be that diagonal,
or will it be one of the other five options?
One more question for you.
If we chucked a weight at the bottom,
which shape would it be?
- Oh. - Probably D.
- B, or possibly C.
- [Derek] Does that change it?
- Then I think it would be B.
- Easy to do on the ground.
Alright, we're dropping the rope over the side.
This one has 20 pound kettlebell off the end of it.
How's that feel when it's dangling?
- No lateral displacement at all.
- Alright.
- How's your forearms doing?
- I'm feeling good, you know.
I feel like this is the easy way, obviously.
Gonna feel different when I gotta pull it up.
- Okay, is it down? - Yup.
Okay, let's give it a shot.
Here the helicopter is flying at nearly a hundred kilometers per hour,
and the rope makes a different shape.
You can clearly see, it looks like an inverted J.
This is option D.
In fact, this is how the question on the qualifying exam originated.
- So, I taught for a semester in Hong Kong,
and we'd go hiking in the new territories.
One of the times I was hiking,
I saw a helicopter fly with a cable beneath it.
It was carrying something to one of the remote parts
of the Hong Kong new territories.
And I saw the shape of the cable
and thought to myself , "That looks a little counter intuitive and very neat.
This might make a good multiple choice question
for the selection exam for the students."
The cable that I saw had a weight hanging on the end,
which gave it a certain curved shape.
When I shared this with the other coaches, another coach,
Andrew Linn , looked at it
and said , "I think the question might even be more fun
if there is no weight on the cable
because that is even harder to imagine."
- [Derek] To understand why the rope makes this shape,
we can use the same analysis as before.
But now we need to add a large weight to the end of the rope.
And this means at the bottom, the tension needs to be almost vertical
to support the weight of the kettlebell,
which has a lot of weight but not much air resistance.
As you go up the rope, the ratio of total air resistance
to weight for everything beneath increases.
So, the rope turns more horizontal in order for the tension
to balance out that increasing air resistance.
- You're more than halfway. You got it.
- [Derek] For the final test,
- [Derek] 对于最后的测试
I wanted to add something to the bottom of the rope that added almost no weight, but significant air resistance.
我想在绳子的底部加上一个几乎没有什么重量，但对空气阻力很敏感的东西
So, I picked a Veritasium flag, of course.
所以当然，我拿了一个真理元素的旗子
So, what do you think about hanging this at the end of the rope?
所以，你觉得这条绳子的尾端会发生什么？
- Well, it's all science experiment for me.
- 对于我来说这些都是些科学研究，因为你搞的这些试验都是在实际操作中不会做出来的
'cause these are all the things you'd never do with a helicopter in a row.
- What would it be the real risks, like tail rotor or this rotor, or both?
- 做这些动作，真正的风险在哪里？是在尾部的马达还是这个马达还是都是？
- Either.
- 都是。
Any kind of this getting into the inner tail rotor
任何这种东西如果跑到了尾部马达里面，那这飞机就无了
would be destruction to the aircraft.
And we 'll start,
我们开始吧
here we go .
走
- [Derek] Now the rope still seems to be pretty straight.
- [Derek] 现在这绳子看起来还是停止的诶
I think it's because the flag
我想这是因为这旗子还不会（对绳子）增加很足够的拉力的原因
isn't actually adding much drag.
Still looks pretty crazy, interestingly.
但有意思的是，这还是看起来挺疯狂的
So, we decided to add a small parachute to the end of the rope.
所以，我们决定去在绳子的尾端加一个小得降落伞
All right, let's try it.
好了，我们来试一下
The concern here was that the parachute
这样做的风险就是这个小降落伞有可能在部署的时候滑到马达里面
could get flipped up into the rotors during deployment.
So, we bundled the shoot up into a backpack.
所以，我们将这个伞打包了起来
- [Craig] Very nicely done.
- [Craig] 做得很棒
- [Derek] Does it deploy more than that?
- [Derek] 这样做有让拉力增加吗？
- [Craig] No, but once we start moving,
- [Craig] 没有，但是一旦我们开始移动，它就将抓住很多的空气
its gonna grab a lot of air.
- [Derek] Now, with the parachute at the end of the rope,
- [Derek] 现在，我们在绳子尾部加了个降落伞之后
it makes a J shape, which is answer C.
绳子就变成了J形，也就是答案C的形状
With extra air resistance at the end of the rope,
随着更多的空气阻力加在绳子的尾端
but not much weight, the tension has to be virtually horizontal.
但（因为在这个点）重力并不是很大 ，（绳子的）张力方向就需要相当接近水平方向
And then as you go up the rope,
然后随着你沿着绳子往上走，空气总阻力与飞机下面东西的重力的比值将会下降
the ratio of total air resistance to weight
for everything beneath decreases.
So, the rope becomes more vertical
所以，绳子就需要变得更垂直来平衡那不断增大的重力
to balance out the increasing weight.
So, depending on what's on the end of the rope,
所以根据在绳子尾部有的东西，你可以得到答案的B、C或者D
you could get answers B , C or D.
Now, if you enjoyed this video, I bet you would also like my bullet block experiment series.
现在，如果你喜欢这个视频，我猜你也会喜欢我的子弹块试验的系列
So, check it out.
所以，来看看吧