Finding scorpions in the desert at night
夜间在沙漠中寻找蝎子
is surprisingly easy.
出乎意料得容易
All you need is an ultraviolet torch
你只需要一个紫外线手电筒
because scorpions are
incredibly fluorescent.
因为蝎子具有令人难以置信的荧光性
Fluorescence means their
bodies absorb ultraviolet light
荧光意味着它们的身体吸收紫外线
and reradiate it in the
visible part of the spectrum.
并将其重新辐射到光谱的可见部分
They glow this bright neon green color.
他们散发这种明亮的霓虹绿色光
But scorpions aren't the
only animals that fluoresce.
但是蝎子不是唯一一种散发荧光的动物
Jellyfish, amphibians,
owls, and even platypus'
水母、两栖动物、猫头鹰甚至是鸭嘴兽
glow under ultraviolet light.
都在紫外线下发光
Part of this video is sponsored
by Capital One Shopping.
More about them at the end of the show.
I'm out here in the desert
near Bakersfield, California,
我现在在加州贝克斯菲尔德附近的沙漠中
looking for scorpions with Carl Kloock,
和 Carl Kloock 一起找寻蝎子
a professor of biology
at Cal State Bakersfield.
他是加州州立大学贝克斯菲尔德分校的生物学教授
He's been researching
scorpion fluorescence
他研究蝎子的荧光性
for over a decade.
已经超过十年
- If you have a black light
it's really pretty easy.
- 如果你有黑光灯的话，这真的十分容易
If they're there, you're
going to spot them.
如果蝎子在那，你就能看见它们
- [Derek] Does he look
like he's in a posture
- 它是否看起来像在摆姿势
to like defend himself?
保护自己？
- [Carl] Yeah, he's not real happy.
- 是的，它不太高兴
- [Derek] Okay.
- 好的
(man chuckling)
- [Carl] I'm going to grab my high-tech
- 在此我要拿出
scorpion catching equipment here.
我的高科技捕蝎装置
It's a tongue depressor with
a yellow highlighter on it.
是一个涂有黄色荧光的压舌板
So it fluoresces in black light.
So you can see where it is.
它在黑光灯下会散发荧光
因此你能看见它在哪
- [Derek] Got it.
- 明白了
(man chuckling)
- [Carl] This technique is usually to put
- 这种技术通常
the vial behind him,
将瓶子放在蝎子身后
then in front of him.
压舌板放在蝎子身前
- [Derek] That was impressive.
- 这令人印象深刻
All right. Should we give it a shot?
好的。我们也试一试？
- [Carl] Just gently pokes him back in.
- 仅仅轻轻地将它戳进去
And they usually just kind of do a little
他们通常会做一些
side crab walk back.
类似螃蟹的侧行
There you go, and just tilt it up.
就这样，把它倾斜起来
- [Derek] Unbelievable.
- 难以置信
(man chuckles)
Unbelievable.
难以置信！
All right. I'm going to get him.
好的，我一定要抓到他
But why are scorpions fluorescent?
但是为什么蝎子有荧光性？
- I've got about 12 hypotheses.
- 我有大约 12 种假说
So you test them one at a time.
一次测试它们中的一种
- [Derek] You've got
12 Hypotheses about why
- 你有关于蝎子为何散发荧光
the scorpions fluoresce?
12 种假说？
- More like six actually,
I was being a little bit...
实际上更像是 6 个
我有点...
Almost all scorpions fluoresce.
几乎所有的蝎子都有荧光性
I haven't seen it myself,
我自己没有亲眼见过
but some that live at living
caves they don't fluoresce
但是有些居住在洞穴中的蝎子不散发荧光
but it's only like one very small group.
但它只是蝎子中非常小的一部分
All the other scorpions fluoresce.
其他所有蝎子都散发荧光
One possibility is just,
this is a Relic Trait.
一种可能性是
这是一种遗留特性
It's something they developed way back
是自他们从这片陆地上诞生
when they first came out on
land and just haven't lost.
就发展出的特性且一直没有丢失
A chemical that has another function
一种有着其他功能的化学物质
that just happens to fluoresce.
正巧会散发荧光
There are plenty of
chemicals that fluoresce.
有许多化学物质都会散发荧光
I mean, we have internal
bodily fluids that fluoresce.
我的意思是，我们体内有会散发荧光的体液
And clearly those are
never exposed to UV light.
而显然，这些从来没有暴露在紫外线下。
So the idea of having a function
所以专门有一个荧光功能的这种想法
for that fluorescence is kind of silly.
有些愚蠢
This fluoresce is about the
same color as a scorpion,
这个荧光颜色和蝎子的荧光颜色一样
but clearly isn't a scorpion.
但他显然不是个蝎子
It's actually a rock.
它实际上是一块石头
The color is a little off.
颜色有点偏
- [Derek] But that is like, what is that?
- 但是它像是。。那是什么？
- It's plastic from Walpole.
它是来自华普的塑料
- [Derek] Huh.
- 呵
You anted to know if the
scorpions were fluorescing
你想知道是否蝎子
in order to attract insects.
是为了吸引昆虫散发荧光
- Right.
- 没错
- [Narrator] So how did you test that?
- 你是怎么测试的？
- What I did was I used preserved
scorpions like these ones
我使用了保存的蝎子，例如这些
and I took half of them and dip them in
拿出其中一半，将他们浸入
UV blocking marine varnish
so they didn't fluoresce.
阻隔紫外线的船舶清漆，这样一来他们不会散发荧光
And then I just used basically flypaper
之后我仅仅使用捕蝇纸
and took those things outside
and set them side by side
将他们放在户外并排摆放
and then found the
number of flying insects
观察各个捕蝇纸
that were caught in each.
捕捉到的飞虫数量
- [Derek] Okay.
- 好的
- [Carl] So we were outside in moonlight
- 我们在户外的月光下
and I did the same experiment,
在新月和满月时候
both under the new moon and the full moon.
做了同样的实验
And so what I found from that was
我从实验中发现
when there was a new moon,
新月之时
there was no difference in the number
散发荧光的蝎子与不散发荧光的蝎子
of insects caught by the fluorescent
捕捉到的昆虫数量
and non-fluorescent scorpions.
没有区别
But under the full moon,
there's nice, bright UV light
但是在满月下，有充足、明亮的紫外光时
available there was a difference
两者数量有差别
and the ones that fluoresce
actually caught fewer insects.
散发荧光的蝎子实际上吸引了更少昆虫
- It seems kind of counterintuitive.
- 这似乎有点违反直觉。
- So that tells me that
my hypothesis was wrong.
- 这意味着我的假说是错的
Which happens a lot.
这常常发生
Basically yeah, they're not using
大体上说，蝎子并不使用他们的荧光
their fluorescence to lure insects.
来引诱昆虫
In fact, the fluorescence is
a bad thing for them in terms
实际上，就其捕捉飞虫的能力而言
of their ability to catch
flying insects, at least.
荧光对它们来说是一件坏事
- Let me ask you this.
- 我问你一个问题
If you find that fluorescence
is counterproductive
如果你发现荧光在某些方面
for the scorpion in some way,
对蝎子是无益的
doesn't that indicate that there
这难道不意味着
has to be something useful?
在某些方面是有用的？
- Exactly. There must be
something that counteracts that.
- 确实。一定有什么可以抵消这一点
- Sort of negative.
- 有点消极
- That negative, yeah.
- 是有点消极
Scorpions are really well
adapted for what they do.
蝎子真的很适应它们的工作
One of the cool things
here is it scorpions
比较酷的一点是
are actually able to
metabolize iron and nickel.
蝎子实际上能够代谢铁和镍。
And in their pincer here
它们的螯这里
and on the tips of their claws,
以及它们的附肢前端
they actually have basically
iron to strengthen that.
它们用铁来强化这些部位
- [Derek] Iron and nickel
at the end of their tail?
- 在他们的尾部末端有铁和镍？
- [Carl] Yeah. Yeah.
- 是的，没错
You can see like the color
here's a little bit different
你可以看出这边的颜色有一点不同
and that's because of the iron.
这是因为铁元素
- [Derek] That seems
very aggressive to me.
在我看来，这只似乎非常具有侵略性。
One of the main things
we're interested in here
我们主要好奇的事情之一是
is how they see.
蝎子是如何看见的
So I've seen two of their eyes.
我看见了他的两只眼睛
- [Carl] So, those are the
median eyes right there.
- 这是它的中眼
- [Derek] Those two dark spots.
- 这两个小黑点
- [Carl] Yeah. There's a cluster
of three eyes right there.
- 没错。这边有 3 个侧眼簇
And of course on the other
side, so they're symmetrical.
另外一边也有，他们是对称的
So they have a total of eight eyes.
所以他们一共有 8 只眼睛
- Can they detect the light
with parts of their body
- 他们能用不是眼睛的身体部位
that are not eyes?
探测光照吗？
- Yeah. Actually they can.
- [Derek] In a 1968 experiment,
researchers put scorpions in
half covered Petri dishes.
Then they exposed them to bright
light and all the scorpions
quickly hid under the covered
part of the Petri dish.
Then the researchers painted
over the eyes of the scorpions.
So they couldn't see and
repeated the experiment.
But when they turned on
the light, 93% of the time,
the blinded scorpions still scuttled over
to the covered side.
The finding was remarkable.
Scorpions don't need their
eyes to detect light.
They can sense it with their bodies.
- That showed that they have what's called
an extra ocular light sense in their tail.
So they can detect light with their tail.
They can't form images, they can't,
but they can detect light.
- The tail of a scorpion can detect light?
- One hypothesis is that they use it
to communicate with one another.
The idea being that
they use it to determine
primarily whether or not
another scorpion out there
is of the same species for mating.
One fairly low probability hypothesis
is that they can use it as camouflage
because they absorb UV light.
If they're sitting on another
surface that absorbs UV light
and you have an organism
that sees in the UV light
like some owls and
things like that can do,
they would tend to blend
in very nicely with that.
So it's a possibility,
but not that many organisms see in UV
and not that many that
eat scorpion, see in UV
so it doesn't seem very likely.
- [Derek] You go for it.
- [Carl] You want me to do it upclose?
- [Narrator] You do it.
- [Carl] Close.
Here you go. See?
There you go, wow.
- One of the ideas is
scorpions came out of the water
from Silurian period long time ago.
And there was a lot
more UV just in sunlight
and things like that then,
because we didn't have
an ozone layer, we didn't have, you know,
all these things that are
blocking UV in our atmosphere now.
And so the one of the idea is that
it actually acts as a sunscreen.
It's way to absorb those
damaging ultraviolet photons
and convert them away into something
and basically keep them from
penetrating into the body
and causing damage.
- [Derek] Go in your hole.
There you go.
You got him.
- And then there have been some other ones
that are a little bit more out there.
One of which being the one that I actually
settled on at the end is that they use it
as part of their sensory
system to detect the presence
of light in the environment.
So this was the later
experiment after I gave up
on the initial idea that
said that didn't work.
So, all I really did in
that one, very simple,
put a scorpion in each
one of these things here
and then put this under ultraviolet light
and exposed it to ultraviolet light.
And so I measured how
long they spent exposed
versus unexposed and how many times
they went back and forth.
- [Derek] And you were testing scorpions
that were fluorescent and not fluorescent.
- [Carl] Right.
So what I did with that was I developed
a technique to remove, or at least reduce
the ability of scorpions to fluoresce
simply by exposing them for long periods
of time to ultraviolet light.
So basically, you're just
kind of taking the chemical
that is causing fluorescence
in their exoskeleton
and your photo bleaching.
- [Derek] So you're kind
of breaking it down?
- [Carl] So basically,
you're making the chemical
not be able to function properly anymore.
What we found is the activity
levels changed significantly.
So when you exposed to UV light,
the non-fluorescence scorpions acted like
they were in the dark.
There was no difference
between their behavior
and the dark and in UV light.
Whereas when UV light
was present for the ones
that can fluoresce, they
reduced their activity levels.
- [Derek] What's the conclusion from that?
- [Carl] The conclusion from that
is that the fluorescents
itself is acting as a way to,
for them to detect the
presence of ultraviolet light.
Another researcher by the
name of Douglas Gaffin,
came up with a great phrase for it.
I wish I'd come up with the
phrase, but I gotta give credit.
He calls it, a whole-body photon detector.
So it's part of their sensory system.
What we don't know is why they want
to detect ultraviolet light so badly
that they've turned their whole
body into a photon detector.
The suspicion is that it
has to do with determining
whether or not they
should come out at night.
- [Derek] The idea is when UV light hits
a scorpion's body, it
fluoresces and the tail detects
this emitted green light
alerting the scorpion
that it is exposed so
it searches for cover.
- [Carl] Scorpions are good at starving
for long periods of time.
They don't need to eat that often.
And coming out and foraging
is dangerous for them.
And so they don't like to come out
when it's a moonlit night.
Typically the only ones you'll
find out in the full moon
are the ones that are really
hungry, really need food.
If they're well fed, they'll stay down.
So they're using that
as basically their cue
in the environment and saying, you know,
okay, this is how bright it is.
So that's a cue as to how
likely I'm being preyed upon.
And then here's how hungry I am.
That's a cue how badly I need
to get out and get some food.
- [Derek] Right.
- [Dr. Carl] And then the
trade off between those two
is basically should I go out tonight
or should I stay in my hole.
- [Derek] Yeah.
(techno sound)
- If you like overpaying
when you shop well,
then don't listen to this next part.
But if you want to save
money, then keep watching.
Because this portion of
the video is sponsored
by Capital One Shopping,
a free browser extension
that will automatically
find the best deals
when you shop online.
It's just two clicks
to install and it works
on all major browsers.
Then whenever you shop,
it'll work away in the background,
comparing prices and testing coupons
to make sure you never
overspend on an item again.
As much as I want to save money,
searching for bargains and
coupon codes is a big hassle
and Capital One Shopping
lets you get the best deals
without having to waste any of your time
finding those deals in the first place.
They all apply automatically at checkout.
They even have their own shopping page
that gathers products from
across different sites
and picks out the cheapest ones
so you can shop directly for
the best deals on the internet
and you don't need to be a
Capital One customer to use it.
This extension is free
for literally everyone.
So you can start saving money right away.
I want to thank Capital One Shopping
for sponsoring this portion of the video.
And I want to thank you for watching.