Your DNA is probably already in a database.
You didn't have to provide a sample or give consent
but the unique sequence
of As, Ts, Gs and Cs that make you you
are searchable nonetheless.
So if you committed a heinous crime
and left a bit of your DNA,
law enforcement could search it in a database
and identify you.
This video includes a discussion of serious crimes
which may be disturbing for some viewers
so I wanted to let you know that upfront,
but I think it's necessary
to talk about these crimes in some detail
for reasons that will become apparent.
In the small town of Visalia, California in the mid 1970s,
one of the state's most prolific criminals got his start.
He repeatedly broke into houses and stole small items
like cash, coins, and jewelry.
He was dubbed the Visalia ransacker
but soon his crimes escalated.
- Six months later in 1976,
he moves up to Sacramento and over
the course of the next three years,
he's moving all across Northern California
committing numerous sexual assaults,
over 50 sexual assaults.
- Here, he was called the east area rapist.
- [Male Reporter] The police are saying lock up tight.
Sacramento's infamous east area rapist may still be in town.
- And then in 1979, he moves down to Southern California,
starting in Santa Barbara and starts killing.
And he was known as the original night stalker
in Southern California.
- [Reporter] Variously known as the east area rapist
and the original night stalker,
these were brutal meticulously planned crimes
that spanned numerous California counties
between 1976 and 1986.
- Police believed that all of these crimes
were committed by the same person
now known as the golden state killer.
How was it known that these were committed
by the same person?
- Investigators were relying on MO.
MO, modus operandi is basically
how a criminal will commit a crime.
- He was wearing some type of a mask or a hood.
He was wearing shorts and a T-shirt.
- The golden state killer had a very distinctive MO
- What he would do is
he would break into a house with a gun,
a house with a man and a woman.
He would tie them up
tell the man I'm gonna put plates on your back.
If I hear those plates move,
I'm going to kill your wife and then kill you,
take the wife into another room and sexually assault her.
Then he would go through the house for however much time,
eating, stealing stuff, stealing little things or whatever
and then he would leave.
- How was he not caught based on fingerprint evidence?
- Well, he didn't leave his fingerprints.
He always wore a mask.
He always had gloves on.
This was an offender that did everything
to prevent himself from being caught.
- [Reporter] The golden state killer has been linked
to at least 12 murders, 50 rapes
and a string of burglaries throughout California.
- All right, how's it going?
- How you doing? - Good.
- So we supply DNA sequencing solutions
to the forensic laboratories that process crime scene DNA.
At a crime scene, there's typically less than a nanogram
of DNA left and it's usually degraded, right?
So it breaks down. - Why is there so little?
at a crime scene?
A nanogram?
- Yes.
- That's insane.
- There's no accident that he stops in 1986.
1986 is when the first DNA case of a murder case
is actually solved with DNA and he's,
I think he's following that and he's saying, you know what,
what I'm doing here, I'm leaving my DNA.
I can't do this anymore.
- [Reporter] Investigator Paul Holes tracked
the golden state killer for decades.
- He couldn't it account for DNA technology
and that really was his big mistake.
That was the critical mistake.
He left his DNA all over California.
And it turns out that in three of the cases,
I had three sexual assault kits and that's where I got
the golden state killer's DNA from Northern California.
- But having the unknown killer's DNA wasn't enough.
They needed to match it to a known sample.
In 1990, the FBI started work
1990年，FBI(美国联邦调查局)
on what would become a national genetic database.
开始建立全国的基因库。
It mainly stores DNA profiles
这个基因库主要记录已被判刑的罪犯
from convicted criminals and persons of interest.
和案件相关人士的DNA档案。
It's called the combined DNA index system
它被称为“联合DNA索引系统”，
or CODIS for short.
缩写是CODIS。
In each of your cells, there are 23 pairs of chromosomes,
你的每一个细胞中，都有23对染色体。
one from your mom and one from your dad.
一对染色体中有一条来自母亲，另一条来自父亲。
And at particular places on some chromosomes,
在某些染色体中的特定位置上，
there are short sections of DNA that repeat
会有一些重复的DNA片段，
like A A T G, A A T G, A A T G, and so on.
像是AATG,AATG,AATG这样。
These are called short tandem repeats or STRs
这些片段被称为“短串联重复序列（STR）”。
and different people have different numbers of repeats.
不同的人有不同数量的重复片段。
Forensic labs produce STR profiles
法医实验室通过计算所有的重复片段总数
by counting up the number of repeats at each location.
来生成STR档案。
Initially, there were only 13 places on the DNA
最初，DNA上只有13个位置的STR会被计数，
where STRs were counted, but in 2017
但2017年的时候，
that was expanded to 20.
这个数量扩大到了20个。
It feels to me like that's not that much information.
我感觉这个档案并没有提供太多有用的信息。
- It isn't.
并不是你认为的这样。
- But the chances of two people having
两个人在所有被计算的位置上，
the exact same number of repeats at all locations
都拥有相同数量的重复片段的概率
is incredibly small.
是非常小的。
The CODIS database now contains
现在，CODIS数据库中，
over 18 million STR profiles.
已经有了超过1800万的STR档案。
- The golden state killer's DNA profile has been up
2001年，金州杀手的DNA档案
at the national DNA database
就被上传到了
that's run by the FBI called CODIS since 2001
FBI建立的国家DNA数据库（CODIS）。
and has been searching ever since with no hits.
自那以后，就一直在找他，但毫无成效。
We did Interpol searching,
我们向国际刑警组织申请，
trying to search other country's DNA databases thinking
尝试在其他国家的DNA数据库中搜索。
well, maybe he came from a out of the country
我们想得很美，
that's why after all this time we have yet
这么久都没确认他的身份，
to be able to identify him
可能是因为他来自其他国家。
and obviously we didn't get any hits.
不过很显然，我们的搜索没有任何收获。
- But genetic sequencing technology was advancing rapidly.
尽管如此，基因测序技术依然发展迅猛。
- [Female Reporter] The human genome project was completed.
[女记者]人类基因组计划已经完成。
Since 1986 scientists had been mapping and sequencing
从1986年开始，科学家们就一直在
the three billion nucleotides contained
绘制和测序人类基因组中的
in the human genome.
30亿个核苷酸。
It's anticipated that
这很让人期待……
- Soon private companies began offering genetic tests
directly to consumers and they provide far more genetic data
than what's in the CODIS database.
I traveled to Houston, Texas
to visit Family Tree DNA headquarters.
- We'll go in the lab and we'll start talking
about the life cycle of a sample.
There you go.
- Thank you.
These samples, what are they?
- So they're cheek cells. They just scrape
the inside of their cheek, they put a cap on it
and they send it back to us.
- It's like a robot ballet.
- Yes, so for DNA extraction,
we need to remove all of the protections that are on the DNA
and just separate it by itself so we can do testing on that.
- Instead of looking at 20 places on your DNA,
these tests examined 700 to 800,000.
- The Family Finder test is based
on what's called a micro array
and this is what a micro array looks like.
Each one of those boxes is an individual.
We can fit 24 individuals on here.
And within that box is about 710,000 positions
of your DNA, that we're measuring, we're getting data for.
- 710,000?
- Yes, and they're called snips.
- So hang on, that's like 710,000
individual bases, like ATGC?
- Yes.
- For each person, you can measure 24 on that single chip?
- Correct.
- The human genome consists of three billion bases.
All people share about 99.9% the exact same DNA,
which means on average, only about three million basis
differ from person to person.
These individual letter changes are known
as single nucleotide polymorphisms or SNPs.
So on there, are there a whole bunch
of like little pieces of DNA then?
- Yes, so what we have is a short piece of DNA
that is specific to one SNP.
So it's one position in the genome
where we know there can be a difference.
- Okay.
Is there any example of a simple SNP
that confers some sort of?
- Actually blue eyes is a single base change.
- Really?
- Yeah.
- So everyone with blue eyes has this one letter change? - mm hmm
- You can see now it's starting to scan the first box.
- The results of your 710,000 SNPs can tell you
about your geographic ancestry
or possible medical conditions,
but they can also quantify
how related you are to someone else.
The genetics of having a kid
are a bit like cutting two decks of cards together.
The resulting deck will share
about half its cards with each parent
and there'll be long sequences of cards
which match identically sequences in each parent.
Now, if this deck has a kid, well then its offspring
will share only about a quarter of its cards
with each grandparent and the sections of identical cards
will be shorter, and this is how it works with DNA.
The more closely you're related to someone,
the more DNA you share and the longer
the blocks of identical DNA are.
But to compare the DNA of two people,
you don't need to read every letter.
The snips are sprinkled throughout the DNA
roughly every 2000 bases.
So if you find long sections where the snips match up,
you can bet that the DNA in between is identical too
by comparing hundreds of thousands of snips sprinkled
throughout the DNA,
you can see where these identical blocks start and stop
and so how much total DNA is shared.
- Everywhere that is highlighted in blue
is where I share DNA.
- With your father? - With my father
which is exactly what you expect
because I should share DNA with him everywhere
because he gave me 50% of my DNA.
So this is a second to third cousin.
I have no idea who this person is.
And you can see here,
we are definitely not as closely related as me and my dad
because where the blue is,
those are the only regions of the chromosome
where we share DNA.
- We all know that these genetic tests
can help identify our relatives but the question is,
can you do the same thing with law enforcement databases?
Can you identify family members using the CODIS database?
- You can and it's only limited
to really first order and second order relatives.
- That means if I'm looking for the golden state killer,
I'm looking for either his father, his brother or his son.
We did that over and over again with no hits.
- Why is it so limited?
- Because you've only got 23 loci.
If you wanna do proper kinship analysis,
you need to have more points assessed on that genome
to see how related you really are.
- We know the answer is behind a locked door
and the answer is behind the locked door
of 23andMe and Ancestry.com.
We know that they have millions of profiles.
Somebody related to him, a second cousin I would guess,
would be in there.
- Sure.
- And that was very hard to deal with.
You know, that the answer is there behind this locked door.
- Law enforcement is not allowed to search
the databases of 23andMe and Ancestry.com
but luckily for investigators, there was another way.
An independent website called GEDmatch had been set up
有人建立了一个名为 GEDmatch 的独立网站
to allow people to connect with relatives.
使人们得以联系到自己的亲戚
You can upload the raw data
你可以上传自己的原始 DNA 数据
from any of the big genetic testing companies
无论它来自哪一间基因检测公司
and search for matches.
并搜索与自己基因相匹配的人
- So when we initially search the GEDmatch database,
在我们开始搜索 GEDmatch 数据库时
our best hits come back at third cousins
匹配最接近的 是他的第三代堂（表）兄妹
which means they shared you know, our top hit,
也就是说，这个人和他共享了
I think shared about 1% of the DNA.
大约 1% 的 DNA
It's very little DNA that's shared
他们共享的 DNA 确实很少
but that's a starting data point.
但这是数据的起点
And theoretically, by taking multiple of these individuals that share DNA
理论上 通过获取多个共享 DNA 的个体
and building their family trees
并且画出谱系图
using traditional genealogy and public source documents
利用传统的基因学和公共来源的文件
like census records and obituaries
比如人口普查记录 讣告
and newspaper articles and findagrave.com,
报刊文章和 findagrave.com
you build this family tree back
向上构建谱系图
until you get two of these relatives
直到在金州杀手的亲属中找到这两个人
you get them to intersect
他们最终交会在同一处
where now you see, oh, they've got,
你会发现
they share great-great grandparents together.
他们有共同的高祖父母
Theoretically the golden state killer is a descendant
理论上 金州杀手也是他们的后代
from those same great-great grandparents.
来自相同的高祖父母
So once I identify that common ancestor,
所以 一旦我确认了他们的共同祖先
it's now identifying every single descendant
接下来要辨认这对高祖父母的每一个后代
from those great-great grandparents
and this becomes a huge process.
这是个巨大的工程
People in the 1840s would typically have 15 kids.
18世纪40年代的人通常有15个子女
You have to identify each of those kids
你得逐个辨认他们的所有子女
and then all of their children
还有这些子女的所有子女
and then all of their children.
依此类推
So now we have this exponentially growing family tree.
于是 就有了一张呈指数增长的谱系图
- How wide did that tree get?
这个谱系图会变得多宽呢？
- I think we had over 1000 individuals in that family tree
我认为 里面有一千多人
but we knew a lot about our offender.
但我们对这个罪犯十分了解
We were confident he was born between 1940 and 1960.
我们确信他生于 20世纪40年代 到 60年代
We knew he was a white male.
他是白人男性
We knew he was 5'8" to 5'10".
他身高介于 5英尺8英寸(1.73m) 和 5英尺10英寸(1.78m) 之间
You know, he's in California.
你也知道 他人在加州
He's up in Sacramento in 1976.
1976年时 他在萨克拉门托
He's in Southern California in the '80s
20世纪80年代时 他在南加州
and we basically narrowed it down to about five males
我们最终将目标范围缩小到五个男性
and then it's just investigations.
然后就是调查了
- With a suspect at their fingertips,
嫌疑人已经触手可及
this spring, they followed him
今年春天，他们跟踪他
to a Sacramento area Hobby Lobby store
前往萨克拉门托的 Hobby Lobby store
and took a DNA sample from his car door handle.
并从他的车门把手上采集到了他的 DNA 样本
Days later, investigators recovered another DNA sample
几天后 调查人员找到了另一份 DNA 样本
from one discarded tissue which registered a match
是从一张丢弃的纸巾上获得的
to DNA evidence left at one of the crime scenes.
它与其中一处犯罪现场遗留的 DNA 痕迹吻合
- Investigators in California say DNA evidence led them
加州的调查人员说  DNA 痕迹引导他们
to one of the country's most notorious serial killers.
找到了美国最臭名昭著的连环杀手
Former police officer Joseph James DeAngelo was arrested yesterday
前警官 约瑟夫-詹姆斯-德安杰罗 昨天被捕
and he is believed to be the so-called golden state killer.
据信 他就是所谓的“金州杀手”
For 44 years, countless investigators have worked it
44年来 无数的调查员致力于破解此案
and have failed to solve it.
无一成功
Within four and a half months, a team of six were able
而一个六人小组，仅用四个半月
to figure out who the golden state killer was
就能找出金州杀手其人
and that was Joseph DeAngelo.
原来是约瑟夫-德安杰罗
- After the golden state killer was identified,
金州杀手被找到以后
the flood gates opened and we were seeing every week
如闸门打开一般 我们每周都能看到
not only single killers, but multiple killers, serial killers
不只单人杀手 还有多人杀手 连环杀手
every week were being identified
每周都有新的凶手被辨认出来
from cases in the '70s and the '80s.
那些七八十年代的悬案得以破解
- 'Cause, there's been over 70 cases now
因此，调查人员现在用这种方式
that they've solved this way
解决了超过70件案子
and they continue to solve them at a fairly regular rate
并且他们依然以一种相当稳定的速率解决案件。
and I think
并且我认为
- Presumably that rate's just gonna increase.
很有可能这一速率只会增加
- Yeah.
是的
- And there's gonna be more because it's working
并且将会有更多，因为这种方法是有效的
and we are going to help find these people.
我们将会帮忙找寻这些人
- But the scary thing is in the US,
但是可怕的是
you have 100,000 cold case murders with DNA.
全美一共有100000起留有DNA的谋杀悬案
You have more cold cases but the ones with DNA
总计的谋杀悬案有更多
is estimated about 100,000
但是留有DNA的估计在100000起左右
There's roughly about 650,000 sexual assaults,
大约有650000起留有DNA的性侵犯悬案
cold cases with DNA. - With DNA?
留有DNA？
It seems like a real paradigm shift.
这似乎像是真正的范式转变
- It is.
它确实是
Multiple law enforcement agencies has said
许多执法部门认为
that this is the most revolutionary tool they've had
这是他们继采用指纹之后
since the adoption of the fingerprint.
用过的最具革命性的工具
- With traditional DNA, it required getting a sample
对传统DNA技术来说，它需要从实际个体
from the actual individual.
获取样本
It's a one-to-one type of process.
这是一种一对一的过程
And so these offenders who let's say
所以这些罪犯
they have committed crimes and haven't been caught
假设他们犯了罪且从未被抓
and they're just living their life and they're thinking,
之后他们过着自己的生活，心里想着
well, my DNA has never been taken from me.
我从来没被提取过DNA
I may have left DNA in the case
我可能在1975年犯下的案子里
that I committed back in 1975,
留下了我的DNA
but they've never gotten my DNA, they won't find me.
但是执法部门没有我的DNA，他们找不到我的
But now we don't have to rely upon that.
但是现在我们不必依赖传统DNA技术了
Somebody distantly related to that offender
如果罪犯的某个远房亲戚
has put their DNA into a database
将自己的DNA录入数据库中
and they have to start getting nervous
罪犯就不得不开始紧张了
because that's outside of their control.
因为这件事不是他们能控制的
They can't account for a third cousin
他们无法了解第三代堂（表）兄妹的情况
or what that third cousin is doing.
也不知道第三代堂（表）兄妹在做什么
And so they start getting nervous.
所以他们开始紧张不安
And I've kind of wondered
我有些好奇
how many of these individuals recognize
这些罪犯中有多少人会意识到
that law enforcement is eventually gonna
因为第三代堂（表）兄妹将他们自己的DNA放入数据库
be knocking on their door as a result
最终会导致执法者
of a third cousin putting their DNA in the database?
敲响他们的房门
- Each person who uploads their information to a database
每个将自己信息上传数据库的人
illuminates the identities
将点亮他们周围
of hundreds of other people around them,
数百个人的身份
parents, siblings, aunts, and uncles and cousins.
父母、兄弟姐妹、姑姑、叔叔和堂兄弟姐妹们
A study by ancestry DNA found the average person in the UK
一项对祖先DNA的研究发现，
has 175 third cousins and it doesn't stop there.
英国人平均有175个第三代堂（表）兄妹，而且还不止于此
The DNA in one person will be shared
一人身上的DNA
by hundreds of people yet to be born.
将共享给数百个尚未出生的人
Children, grandchildren, nieces, and nephews,
子女、孙子女、侄子/孙女、外甥/外甥女
and cousins once or twice removed.
甚至是差一个或者是两个辈分的表亲
Realistically, each person shares identifiable DNA
现实中，每个人都与过去与未来的近1000人
with nearly 1000 people past and future.
共享可被识别的DNA
So it doesn't take many people uploading their data
不需要许多人上传他们的数据
to reveal the identities of everyone living in a country.
就能显示出生活在一个国家的所有人的身份
Back in 2018, a study found that using an existing database
在2018年，一项研究发现
of just 1.3 million people, they could identify 60%
使用现存的130万人口的数据库，
of all Americans of European descent.
他们能够确认出60%的欧裔美国人
And they estimated with a database containing
他们仅仅是用包含了人口总数的2%的数据库
just 2% of the population, you could find a third cousin
进行估计，就能在99%的测试例中找到
or closer match in 99% of cases.
第三代堂（表）兄妹或者更亲的血缘关系
- DNA storage is one of the things that we have
that is really unlike anything else.
If you look inside, this is at minus 20 degrees Celsius.
- That keeps the DNA good for a long time?
- We have DNA samples in here
that are probably about 15 years old.
- How many samples are stored in there?
- Just over 2 million.
- Wow. - Yeah.
So the capacity is just over 2 million.
- 2 million people's DNA stored in this one small room?
- Correct.
- Wow.
By 2021, over 30 million people worldwide
have taken a direct consumer genetic test,
the majority of which are through Ancestry and 23andMe,
which do not currently work with law enforcement
but Family Tree DNA does.
- If you ask Americans, should we have a national database
where everyone's logged in it?
- As their DNA?
- Yeah by their DNA and their name,
most Americans will be somewhat uncomfortable
or potentially very uncomfortable with that.
But we're kind of sleepwalking into that scenario.
- There are some people who are concerned with privacy.
If anyone chooses or decides
that they do not want their results
to be used for law enforcement matching,
they can remove themselves from that.
- I do worry about genetic information being used
to discriminate against someone.
- My biggest thing is health insurance.
I worry about if you have somebody's DNA profile
and some laws enacted, it gets in the wrong hands
and they say that this person has a proclivity,
they're headed towards Parkinson's,
they're headed towards this, headed towards that
and then rates skyrocket.
That's the biggest place that I see as a privacy concern.
- Once your genetic information is out there,
it's out there.
It's not like a credit card where you can get a new one.
Yeah you're giving away something
that you don't know what it can do.
- Well, yeah our information isn't ours
in the first place. - Right.
- Our information is shared.
- Yes with your relatives.
- Yes. - And although you may be
adverse to this sort of thing,
if they've already done it, if it,
you know, in a way you're out there.
- In society today, you have very clearly had two camps.
There are those that are very comfortable
having their genome available to be able to be searched
for law enforcement purposes
and there are others that are not comfortable at all
and that's okay.
- The problem is of course,
those people who don't want theirs to be searchable
could have their DNA uploaded inadvertently
by their relatives.
Do you know what I mean?
So like, if I don't want my DNA
to be searchable by law enforcement
but my sister uploads hers, - Yes.
- It's almost as good as me doing it myself.
- Right now, Family Tree DNA's policy
is we only accept samples from law enforcement
under certain circumstances.
It has to be a sexual assault, identification of remains,
DNA recovered from the scene of a homicide.
And we also do child abductions.
So if there's a child that's kidnapped
and there's DNA evidence, we will process the DNA
so that they can try to find out who the abductor is.
Those are the only cases that we will accept.
- Got it.
- Unfortunately now GEDmatch has flipped off the switch
and GEDmatch has actually said that you don't all have
to have your information searched without opting in.
- Right.
- Was that decision by GEDmatch
a direct result of this golden state killer case?
- No, it wasn't. - No.
- Wanna tell the story?
- You know, it had to do with a Utah case.
- Where an elderly woman was playing the organ in a church.
- And there was an individual who broke in
and assaulted her.
- But it wasn't a sexual assault, but it's a serious crime.
- I think believed, tried to strangle her
and left her for dead.
I believe he thought that she was obviously dead and left.
The police I believe approached GEDmatch
because that they were concerned
that he was going to recommit other crimes.
- But GEDmatch's terms of service said
they would only help law enforcement
in cases of rape or homicide.
- Her problem was that she didn't die.
- 'Cause if she died then?
- If she died it would have fit the conditions
and then they would have uploaded the sample
because it met the terms
of service and everything. - So what happened?
They didn't take that case?
- They did.
- They subsequently caught the individual
from that search that they performed on GEDmatch.
- But people within the genealogy world kinda got
their passions and flame saying that is stepping outside
of what this tool should be used for
and they ended up putting a lot of pressure on GEDmatch.
- They flipped the switch because they got freaked out.
- But at the end of the day,
it was a violation of terms of service.
And I think ultimately led to a good thing.
Everybody got zeroed out
and then everybody gets to sign back in.
- Subsequently GEDmatch was sold to Verogen.
- I can tell you a new user today
when they sign up for GEDmatch, about 73% of them
are signing up to allow law enforcement to search.
We're pretty happy with that.
- Yeah I mean, that's, it's a high number.
- It's a high number.
- And it suggests that people want that innocence.
- How many second cousins or third cousins do you now?
You know what I mean?
You don't know that many of them.
Without even knowing it, you're helping justice.
You're helping a victim's family get a little bit of peace,
not closure, but a little bit of peace
and why not? - They get an answer.
- Partly, you could make an argument
that if you wanna be an activist helping catch criminals,
one of the best things you can do
is encourage everyone you know to be tested
and put in the database.
- Correct and you know, there are millions
of people who have tested at other companies
that are not working with law enforcement.
And if they want to help, all they have to do
is download their raw data and they can upload it for free
into our database.
- I absolutely believe in a person's right to privacy.
But I also absolutely believe we have a right not
to get murdered or sexually assaulted or it will be part
having violent crimes committed against us.
There has to be an equal balance.
- That scale of my privacy has been taken
because of a third cousin has been identified
versus a mother who's talking
about her daughter has been murdered,
that scale is way the hell like this.
- We're at a point now where in many ways technology
has kind of outstripped where the laws are.
I truly believe that ultimately this tool and the,
all the concerns with it will probably end up
in front of the nation Supreme Court
and there will be a decision.
My bottom line message, if you're gonna make a decision,
if there's gonna be laws restricting law enforcement
to use it, make sure that you're making an informed decision
and not assuming what it is based on
its DNA and genetics and law enforcement
because it really isn't what you think it is.
- I gotta keep a couple of million people happy
so that I have access to the identities, kind of in a sense.
- In a sense, right? - Of millions,
of hundreds of millions of people.
- Right.
- And that's a pretty selective sample.
These are people who are willing
to give up their information - Give up, yes.
- To find their ancestors. - Yeah.
- There may be many others who are militantly private
but they don't get a say in the decision
of whether they're gonna be searchable
through that person or not.
- True, that's the choice you make.
- That's the choice you don't make.
- It's a choice you don't make but it's also
it's the choice we have to make as a society,
is what's that balance.
There is always gonna be winners and loses
in my mind, right?
And I don't wanna use losers in the negative sense there
but in a decision at the end of the day,
you have to balance in my mind
the public safety with the public privacy.
- Is DuckDuckGo, is that good?
- I use it.
I'm a little paranoid.
So it's supposed to not track you as much I guess, but yeah.
- I have been working on this video for a couple of years
so I really wanna thank Brilliant for sponsoring it.
I appreciate their willingness
to support me tackling complex and important stories.
Brilliant is a website, an app
that teaches you all kinds of stem concepts
in an interactive and in-depth way,
if you wanna learn more about DNA
or solving mysteries with deductive reasoning,
I would recommend their courses
on computational biology and logic.
Check out this interactive logic puzzle.
You have to figure out if the light is on or off,
knowing that some of the characters may be lying to you.
And instead of just telling you the solution,
Brilliant allows you to try different configurations
and discover the answer for yourself.
And if you get stuck, there are helpful hints
to guide you along the way.
In this instance, the light is on,
see if you can figure out why.
Now Brilliant is offering 20% off an annual subscription
to the first 200 people to sign up.
Just go to brilliant.org/veritasium.
I will put that link down in the description.
So I wanna thank Brilliant for supporting Veritasium
and I wanna thank you for watching.