- Can I tell you something I'm bad at?
- 可以告诉你一件我不擅长的事情吗？
I am terrible at making clickbait.
我非常不擅长当“标题党”。
Up until two years ago,
在两年前那会
my most popular video
was about a basketball
我最火的视频是一个关于把回旋的篮球
being dropped from a dam
with a bit of backspin.
从水坝上扔下来的视频
It takes off like a rocket and shoots out
篮球像火箭一样发射出去
way further than you'd expect.
比你想象的远得多。
This video was embedded
这个视频被嵌入到几百个新闻网站中
on literally hundreds of news websites.
And in its first week, it
got 16.3 million views,
在视频发出一个星期内获得了一千六百万次浏览，
but almost none of those views
came on the YouTube platform.
但几乎没有浏览是来自 YouTube 平台本身。
Why?
为什么？
Because I gave it this thumbnail
因为这是我给它的封面，
and I called it "Strange
Applications of the Magnus Effect."
并且我把这个视频取名为”马格努斯效应的奇怪应用“。
This video is sponsored by KiwiCo.
More about them at the end of the show.
Now, I believe within YouTube,
我相信，我现在在 YouTube 被认作
I'm used as an example of how
not to package your video.
不去”包装“自己视频的典型例子。
As if to demonstrate just how bad
有一个人重新上传了这一视频并
将它取名为”从水坝扔下的篮球“
a title and thumbnail this is,
someone else re-uploaded the
video with the clever title,
"Basketball Dropped From Dam."
就像是为了凸显原来的标题和封面有多烂。
And within a few weeks,
that video had received
几个星期内，这个视频就在 YouTube 上
tens of millions of views on YouTube.
获得了几千万浏览。
This is when YouTube gave
me access to ContentID.
这时候 YouTube 给了我 ContentID 的使用权限。
That's the system that
allows you to earn revenue
这个系统能够让你在别人转载你的视频时赚取收益。
when someone else re-uploads
your videos, which was good,
but I still wasn't very good at clickbait.
这很不错，但我还是不擅长当标题党。
So for this video, I called in an expert.
所以制作这期视频时，我请了一位专家。
I wanted to see your reaction face.
我想看看你的震惊脸。
Can you give me like a reaction face?
能否让我看看你的震惊脸？
Like what's a good thumbnail face?
比如一个适合作为封面的表情长什么样？
- Oh, I got you.
哦，我明白你的意思了。
This is a thumbnail face.
这是一个用作封面的表情。
(Derek laughs)
(Derek 大笑)
I have like 10, I go through
the motions of like...
我有十个这样的表情，就比如像这样
(Derek laughs)
(Derek 大笑)
And then we just take the best one,
然后我们选择最好的一个
I probably have like
500 of these just saved
我大概存了五百个像那样的表情
and we can just Photoshop
my face on my face.
然后我们直接 PS 这些表情。
That way, I don't have to do it anymore.
这样我就不用再做表情了。
- When I started on this
platform, some 10 years ago,
大约十年前，当我刚加入这个平台时
clickbait was less important.
标题和封面没那么重要。
Subscribers were what mattered,
重要的是关注，
because most of the views
came from the sub feed.
因为大部分的点击都来自向关注者的推送。
And videos went viral usually
视频爆红一般是靠其他地方的流量，
by getting a lot of attention elsewhere,
like on Reddit or Facebook,
比如 Reddit 和 Facebook，
not due to the YouTube algorithm.
而不是靠 YouTube 的算法。
But once you had a big
video and people subscribed,
但一旦你有了一个比较火的视频，吸引人们关注，
well, then your next video
would likely get a lot of views
那你的下一个视频很可能就会从关注者那里得到很多浏览。
from those subscribers.
So YouTube would take that popular video
于是 YouTube 就会把热门的视频
and share it with more people.
分享给更多人。
And so you'd get more subscribers
这样你会获得更多的关注者
in a positive feedback loop.
形成一个正反馈循环。
But soon, YouTube realized
that this did not create
但很快，YouTube 认识到这样不能为观众
the best experience for the viewer.
提供一个最优的体验。
They discovered that
showing people only videos
它们发现，光给人们展示他们订阅频道的视频
from channels they were
subscribed to led to fewer clicks,
导致整个网站作为一个整体
less watch time and less engagement
点击数、观看时间、互动量较少。
with the site as a whole.
Plus, they knew that
relying on other platforms
况且，他们知道依靠其他平台
to drive traffic to viral hits was risky,
引导流量创造爆红视频有风险
since those other platforms might disable
因为这些平台可以随时
the traffic at any time.
砍掉这些流量。
So they needed to make YouTube
a destination in itself.
所以他们要让 YouTube 本身成为流量目的地。
They wanted people to come to YouTube,
他们希望人们来到 YouTube，
see videos that interested them,
看他们感兴趣的视频，
click on at least one of them
and watch it for a while.
点击其中至少一个视频并看一段时间。
Ideally get sucked down
the YouTube rabbit hole
最好掉进 YouTube 的陷阱里
and spend hours on the site
without even noticing it.
不知不觉地在网站上花费数个小时。
The ultimate resource is people's time
最终极的资源还是人们的时间
and attention, and every platform
和注意力，而每个平台
is trying to capture as
much of it as possible.
都希望获取尽可能多的资源。
So, to make YouTube
this go-to destination,
因此，为了让 YouTube 成为这个目的地，
they had decrease the
importance of subscribers,
它们减少了关注的重要性，
make it less like a podcast app
让它不像一个播客应用那样
where you only get the
shows you're subscribed to,
只能收听你已经关注的节目，
and more like Reddit,
而是更像 Reddit，
where stuff with the most
engagement rises to the top.
互动最多的东西被顶到最前面。
But that necessarily meant increasing
但那必然意味着提高标题和封面的重要性。
the importance of clickbait.
Now, there seems to be a paradox
when it comes to clickbait.
但关于”标题党“却有一个矛盾。
People almost universally
claim to hate it,
几乎所有人都声称自己讨厌它，
but you also see it everywhere.
但你在哪里都能看到它。
So why is this?
那这是为什么？
Well, one of the problems
is we don't all agree
好吧，一个问题是我们没有在”标题党“
on the definition of clickbait.
的定义上达成一致。
When I google it, the top definition is,
我去搜索它时，第一条定义是，
on the internet, content
whose main purpose
在互联网上，用于吸引注意力、鼓励访客
is to attract attention
and encourage visitors
to click on a link to
a particular webpage.
点击某个网页链接的内容。
We could call this type I clickbait,
我们可以把它叫做”Ⅰ类标题党“，
and there doesn't seem to
be anything wrong with it.
而且它本身似乎没有什么错。
I mean, if you didn't
try to attract attention
我的意思是，如果你不去吸引注意力
and get people to click on your links,
并让人们点击你的链接，
then you wouldn't really
be doing your job.
那等于没做你该做的事。
But there is a second definition.
但它还有第二种定义。
One that I think more people ascribe to,
一种我认为有更多人理解的定义。
which is something such
as a headline designed
一个让读者想去点击网页链接的东西，比如标题
to make readers want to
click on a hyperlink,
especially when the link leads to content
尤其是链接到内容可疑的网页时。
of dubious value or interest.
Wikipedia says, "A defining
characteristic of clickbait
维基百科说：”标题党的一个根本特征是
is that it is sensationalized
or misleading."
情绪化或有误导性。“
And it also talks about teasers
它还提到了一种标题
that intentionally withhold information
故意去隐藏信息
to exploit the "curiosity gap."
来利用你的好奇心。
They give you enough
information to make you curious,
它给你足够多的信息来激发你的好奇心
but not enough to satisfy that curiosity.
但不足以满足你的好奇。
Here are two actual titles
from a news website.
这里是某新闻网站上的两个标题。
Nine out of 10 Americans
are completely wrong
《十个美国人有九个完全搞错了
这一惊人的事实》
about this mind blowing fact.
And someone gave some kids some scissors.
《一个人给一些孩子几把剪刀，接下来发生了这些》
Here's what happened next.
I think we can all agree
that these are examples
我觉得我们都会认可它们属于
of bad type II clickbait.
坏的第二类标题党。
Now, imagine a clickbait
space where on one axis,
you have how misleading
or sensationalized it is.
And on the other, how much information
is intentionally withheld
to create a curiosity gap.
Well, then these two titles
fall in the top right corner.
And these are the zones
of type II clickbait.
At the other extreme,
you have things that are so
unsensationalized as to be dull.
You could call this the dead zone.
Now, here is where you would find
"Strange applications
of the Magnus Effect."
I mean, I didn't tell you
what the applications were.
Now, in the middle is where you
would find type I clickbait.
But honestly, I think type
I and type II clickbait
are so different, that
we shouldn't even use
the same word for them.
Instead of type I clickbait,
my friend and YouTuber, Brady
Heron suggested legitbait.
I mean, it might sound
enticing, but it is legit.
Instead of type II clickbait,
we could use clicktrap,
clicktrick, linktrap or dupechute.
What's important to recognize
is that for any given video,
there is no one true title and thumbnail.
Each video could have
hundreds or thousands
of different legitbait titles.
For example, how does a zero-G plane work?
I went on a plane that does
parabolic trajectories.
What happens to fire on a zero-G plane?
Now, the most enticing
titles and thumbnails
are found close to type II clickbait.
I'm reminded of the infographic
by smarter every day,
showing that on social media,
the greatest engagement
occurs close to the boundary
of what's allowable.
But remember that everyone's
definition of clickbait
is different, and everyone's perceptions
of words and images are different.
So these are not clear boundaries.
They're actually kind of fuzzy.
What for one person might be legitbait,
for someone else, could be a clicktrap.
What's clear is that on a site
where click-through rate is important,
clickbait of all types is inevitable.
How important to a video's success
is the title and thumbnail?
- Very important. Of course.
If they don't click on the video,
they don't watch it.
You can't get 10 million views
unless 10 million people
click on the video.
So, I mean, it's literally that simple.
They don't click on it,
they don't watch it.
- So, why is clickbait everywhere?
Well, because it works.
More enticing thumbnails get more clicks.
Despite some people's claims
that they won't click or they'll unsub,
it's just like evolution.
Whatever survives, multiplies
and traits become amplified.
If you don't begrudge
the giraffe its long neck
so it can reach the highest leaves,
can you begrudge a YouTuber the red arrow
that allows them to
reach further audiences?
I talked about this in
my video two years ago.
To be successful as a YouTuber,
you need to optimize two things,
watch time and the click-through
rate of your videos.
That's the number of times
the title and thumbnail are clicked,
divided by the total number
of times they're shown.
That's the number of impressions.
Now at the time,
this was something of a revelation for me
because I always thought my
job was to make great videos.
And then a title and thumbnail
that adequately represented
what the video was about.
But now I've realized that
making the title and thumbnail
is at least half the job.
This is not just because
better titles and thumbnails
get you more clicks,
but because better titles and thumbnails
will get you way more impressions.
YouTube has limited real estate
with which to show you
virtually infinite content.
And so it's not enough
to make a good video
even if people watch all of it,
you also have to make
a title and thumbnail
that gets clicked,
especially in competition
with other really good
titles and thumbnails.
That's the only way you can expect YouTube
to give you more impressions.
Now, the big development
since my last video on this
is YouTube introduced real-time metrics
like views, impressions
and click-through rate.
Now, I suggested this
would create an arms race.
So what you can bet will happen
is that creators will launch a video
and then they'll be sitting there
with all these different
variants of thumbnails
and they'll be swapping them out
and looking at what that
does to click-through rate
and then going with the one
that leads to the greatest
click-through rate.
And this is basically what has happened.
Let me give you my favorite example.
Last year, I made a video about asteroids,
which I thought was really good.
I called it "Asteroids:
Earth's Biggest Threat,"
which is something Stephen Hawking said.
And people were very
positive about the video.
They thought it was maybe one of my best,
but the performance
was well below average.
In its first day,
asteroids was ranked ninth
out of my previous 10 videos.
It was probably on target
for about one and a half million views.
So I tried different titles and thumbnails
like, "Asteroid Impact:
What Are Our Chances?"
Or "Asteroid Impact: What Could We Do?"
But none of these changes
got much traction.
And then on day three after launch,
I changed the title and thumbnail
to "These Are the
Asteroids to Worry About."
And immediately the video
started doing better.
It quickly shot up from almost
my worst performing video
to my best.
It now has 14 million views.
Nothing about the video changed,
just that one image and 38 characters.
But because of that, the video has reached
nearly 10 times as many people
as it otherwise would have.
And the title and thumbnail
accurately describe
what the video is about.
I mean, sure, there's a curiosity gap,
but you couldn't explain the whole concept
in the length of the title.
So if you see a YouTuber
changing titles and thumbnails,
this is why.
Because that effort can be
rewarded many times over.
I've seen people
objecting to this practice
because they think the creator
is trying to dupe their audience,
get them to click on the
same video more than once,
but that's not it.
The whole point is to get YouTube
to show the title and
thumbnail to more people.
We're trying to increase
the number of impressions,
which is heavily dependent
on the click-through rate.
Now, a lot of my recent videos
have this typical view curve.
There's an initial spike
after I release the video
and then a dip, and then a second bump
after I have figured out a
better title and thumbnail.
I change the title and thumbnail
and I watch the real time view graph.
What I'm looking for is a
noticeable bump in views.
Sometimes there's no change,
sometimes it gets worse,
but on occasions, when you
see something like this,
well then, you know you've found a winner.
This is something all the
big YouTubers are doing.
Not even Mr. Beast knows exactly
which thumbnail will work best beforehand.
Have you ever changed
a title and thumbnail
and then the video did better?
- Oh, of course.
So everybody, I usually make
like two or three thumbnails,
and then if it's not
doing as well as I want,
we usually just swap 'em out
and see if it does better.
'cause the thing is like,
you don't really know.
I mean, you could know if you
just were an almighty being
that could just predict what
people would be interested in,
but you know, usually...
Like, you can do hide and seek.
You don't really know if
like you hiding in a tree
and then someone walking
below you is a good thumbnail.
Or if you hiding a trash can and
them walking in front of you.
So, you know, just do both
and then see which one interests
people a little bit more.
- I feel the same way,
but I do feel like you have a better sense
of this than like most people.
- Of course.
I mean, no one gets 40
million views a video.
(both laughing)
- But what is the point
in getting more views?
If you're cynical,
you might say it's all
about money and fame.
And while there are certainly
financial incentives
to getting more views,
that's not why I do it.
As an educational YouTuber,
I think there are two very good reasons
for using excellent type I clickbait
over more straightforward packaging.
To understand the first reason,
let's consider two
different possible titles
for my most recent video.
I called it "The Simplest Math
Problem No One Can Solve,"
but it's a video about
the Collatz conjecture.
So perhaps a more straightforward title
would have been simply to call it that.
The problem is, if I publish a video
called the Collatz conjecture,
the most likely people to click on it
are those who already know
what the Collatz conjecture is.
And the vast majority of people
will never have heard of it.
So for them, the title is meaningless
and only the very curious
or those who really like
Veritasium would click.
In contrast, calling it
"The Simplest Math Problem
No One Can Solve,"
conveys more information
about the video to everyone.
And this means more
people can click on it,
most of whom will never have heard
of the Collatz conjecture.
So I get to teach them something new.
And since the video has a
higher click-through rate,
YouTube shows it to even more people.
So if my aim is to increase
the level of knowledge
in the world by the
maximum amount possible,
this is the way to do it.
The second reason we need to
optimize titles and thumbnails
is to support the major
goal of this channel.
We are trying to make
the best science films
on every topic we tackle.
That means traveling to meet
experts in film experiments,
hiring people to build props,
make spectacular animations,
research and fact check.
We hire expert consultants
to double and triple check our work.
I don't wanna make vlogs.
I wanna make science
documentaries on YouTube
that put broadcast to shame.
And to make this possible and sustainable,
并且为了让这个目标能够实现且能长期保持下去
the videos have to get
views and lots of them.
我的视频就要有播放量 而且是非常多的那种
And to do that, we have to make
那么既然要这么做 那我们就得
the best titles and thumbnails we can.
想出足够好的标题和封面
YouTuber and Patreon CEO, Jack Conte
Jack Conte, Patreon 的 CEO，也是一位 YouTuber,
has talked about adjusting your packaging.
讲到了关于如何包装视频的问题
The idea is know what
you're passionate about,
具体的意思是指 要清楚你最热衷于什么
what you won't compromise on
不会对什么妥协
and that stuff goes in the box.
把这些核心的东西装在盒子里
All the rest, like what
paper it's wrapped in,
其余的那些 比如用什么样的纸来包这个盒子
that's the packaging.
这就是包装的问题了
So the video is my focus
and the title and thumbnail
那就可以这么讲，视频内容是我最专注的，而标题和封面
are the packaging that
I'm happy to adjust,
则是视频的漂亮包装 我可以随意去调整它
so I can make the type of
videos that are important to me.
如此一来 我才能制作出我心目中地位甚高的视频
Now, is it ironic that a
channel whose whole purpose
那么 如果现在有个频道
is to promote a true seeking mindset
它旨在为人们培养求真心理
has to experiment at the
edge of what is truthful
但它得在真理的边缘疯狂地不计后果地试探
in order to fulfill that purpose?
来达到它的目的，这不是很讽刺吗
It is something that I
often worry about.
这是我通常会担心到的问题
You know, when I did like
risking my life to do X,
你知道，当我确实喜欢冒险去做一件事
it's like, well, what probability of death
那时候我就想着“行吧 得有多大可能会没命
does there have to be for
you to risk your life?
才会让我冒生命危险去做这个事情呢”
Like 50%?
比如 50%？
- I love how he always overthinks things.
- 我很喜欢的是 他总会把事情想的很复杂
(laughs)
That's funny.
（笑）真的很好玩
He's like, is my life risked enough
他就这么想的“我是不是已经快到没命的边缘了
where I can put I risked my life?
所以才来冒生命危险呢
I only had a 9% chance of dying
我大概只有 9% 的可能会没命
and I need at least a 13% chance.
但我需要它至少是 13%”
You're so funny.
这也太好玩了
He was the same way two years ago
两年前他也是这样
when he asked me all this stuff.
问的我这些问题
I was like, "Dude, just do
whatever makes the most sense.
我那时就想“得了吧小伙子 干点有意义的事情它不好吗”
- Yeah, I mean, obviously
I feel like my instincts
- 嗯，确实，是说我有时候觉得我的直觉
are not good.
并不是那么准
But what I realized
但我后来意识到
is that I don't have
to trust my instincts.
我并不需要相信我的直觉
This problem of getting the
best title and thumbnail,
关于什么样的封面和标题可以吸引眼球
well, it's a scientific problem.
实际上 这是个比较科学的问题
We're just asking which accurate
representation of the video
问题其实就是 怎样准确地描述这个视频
will get the most clicks
from a general audience.
才能有更高的可能让普通大众点进来呢
And that's a problem we can use
这就是我们可以用科学方法
the scientific method to solve.
来解决的问题
So I've hired a couple
of really bright people
所以我请来了几个有头脑的人
and we spend a lot of time brainstorming
一起花了很久的时间进行大脑风暴 集思广益
and making titles and
thumbnails and testing them out.
想出有意思的标题和封面 并把它们用在视频上
For example, on Twitter and Patreon.
比如在 Twitter 和 Patreon 上
Varitasium titles and
thumbnails have gotten better,
我们的标题和封面的点子越来越惊奇
not because I'm better at it,
不是因为我在这方面更上手了
but because of my team and our testing.
而是因为我的团队智慧 和我们所做的一系列测试的总结
If you have ideas about
how we could do it better,
如果你有让我们的播放量暴涨的点子
please get in touch.
请联系我们
The results have often
contradicted what I expected.
不过有时候结果和我的期望恰好相反
I mean, this video seemed
to perform 10% better
比如看这个视频 在我把“惊人的”这个词
when we excluded the word
surprising from the title.
从标题里面拿掉之后 播放量较之前多了 10%
So it became simply The Secret of Synchronization.
此时它就是“同步之秘”
I thought these two titles were basically a toss up,
我原以为这两个标题就是个二选一
but Patreon had a strong
preference for one over the other.
但 Patreon 告诉我其中一个很受欢迎
What's interesting about this research
而对于这个研究 非常有趣的是
is that the more clickable
titles and thumbnails
一个能吸引人们点击的标题和封面
often better represent
the content of the video.
通常都能够更好地表达视频内容的主题
Let me give you some examples.
来看几个例子
One thing I didn't expect
when YouTube brought in
在 YouTube 上线实时统计数据分析功能
the real time analytics tools
并允许更改视频的封面和标题
and allowed title and thumbnail changes
来获得人们印象的时候
to affect impressions,
我没想到的是
was that it would also
work for older videos.
老视频同样可以这么做
So here is an old video
that I originally entitled,
这是我最初给一个老视频起的标题
"Why the Neutron is the
Hero of Nuclear Physics."
“中子为何是核物理之英雄”
In hindsight, it's a weird,
kinda meaningless title.
事后看来 这个标题显得很奇怪且毫无意义
So I changed it to, "Why Einstein Thought
所以我把这个标题换成了
Nuclear Weapons Impossible."
“爱因斯坦为什么会认为核武器是不存在的”
It's clearer, more accurate.
这个标题更清晰 也更精确
And this is what happened
to views after the change.
然后这是我改了标题之后播放量的变化
I changed "Strange Applications
of the Magnus Effect"
我把“马格努斯效应的奇怪用法”
to "Backspin Basketball Flies Off Dam."
改成了“在水坝上来一个后旋投篮”
Again, more accurate.
一样更精确的标题
And the video is now
being watched on YouTube.
然后现在这个视频在 YouTube 上非常火
Probably 10 million more views
比我修改标题之前
than it otherwise would have had.
涨了 1000 多万播放量呢
Even anti-clickbait has proven effective.
事实证明非标题党类型的标题也是可以发挥作用的
Here's a video I originally titled,
这是我最初给这个视频起的名字
"Are Negative Ions Good For You?"
“负离子对人真的有好处吗”
Which is a question nobody asked ever.
这是个此前没人问过的问题
Now, I changed it to,
"Do Salt Lamps Work?"
然后我改成了“离子灯对人真的有用吗”
（没用.jpg）
Seriously.
认真讲
And here's the result:
这就是它换了名字的结果
One and a half million more views.
涨了 150 多万播放量
I think looking at these examples,
我觉得 通过观察这些变化
you could easily make the case
你可以很容易得出结论
that YouTube has made
me better at what I do.
YouTube 让我在制作视频这方面更上一层楼
It has improved the clarity and accuracy
它使我的标题和封面
of my titles and thumbnails.
It's helped me figure out
可能胡更加清楚准确 还让我清楚了
what is interesting to my audience
我的观众们所感兴趣的东西
and how to encapsulate
that in a single image
以及将它概括在一个
and fewer than 50 characters.
50 词不到的标题和一张图里面
For those of you who worry that a focus
而对于那些认为我专注于标题和封面
on titles and thumbnails will prevent me
可能会让我选一些
from picking challenging science topics,
不那么有挑战性的科学话题的人们来说
well, I simply ask you
to look at the videos
我觉得，我还是要请你们去看看我们
from the last year or two,
最近两年多发布的视频抓住
like the ones on Gödel's
incompleteness theorem,
比如那个讲哥德尔不完备定理的视频
general relativity, Penrose tilings,
还有广义相对论 彭罗斯瓦解
the logistic map, Newton's
method of calculating Pi,
单峰映射 还有牛顿的计算圆周率近似值的方法
the one way speed of light.
和测量单程光速的视频
Good titles and thumbnails
make it possible
好的标题封面可以紧扣主题
to tackle these topics
and to reach more people
能让这个视频出现在更多的已经知道
who have heard of them before.
或听说过这个东西的人的屏幕上
There is a symbiotic relationship
视频的播放量和视频内容的质量之间
between views and video quality.
有着紧密的相互依存的联系
The more views we get, the more people,
因此，有了更多的播放量，我们才能付出更多的人力
locations, props and equipment
使用更多更好的场地 道具和设备
and research we can invest in.
并进行更缜密的研究
This makes the next video
better than the last.
这才能让下一期视频的质量比之前任何一期都要好
If we can be good at
titles and thumbnails,
那么如果我们可以掌握想出好的标题封面的方法
the ultimate outcome is better videos.
那么最终一定就能做出更好的视频
That is something I think
you and I both want.
我认为这就是你我共同追求的目标
Hey, this video is sponsored by KiwiCo,
a long time supporter of the channel.
Now KiwiCo makes awesome
hands on projects for kids,
including big kids like me.
They have eight subscription lines
targeted at different age groups,
all the way down to newborns.
What I love about KiwiCo crates
is that they make learning fun
and something to look forward to.
I mean, when I pull out a crate,
my kids just jump at the
chance to make it with me.
And all the materials you
need come right in the box.
So there's no need to run to the store.
You just open it up and go.
My kids and I just built
this domino machine,
which, who knows, might be
inspiration for a viral video.
Now, the big idea is that
while playing and having fun,
kids learn about STEAM concepts.
That is science, technology,
engineering, art and math.
And in addition to the project,
there's a magazine with a lot
of additional information.
So I think this is the best way to learn.
By doing something
yourself and having fun,
it's how education should be.
So if you wanna try it out,
go to Kiwico.com/veritasium50,
and you'll get 50% off your
first month of any crate.
I will put that link
down in the description.
So I wanna thank KiwiCo
for sponsoring Veritasium,
and I wanna thank you for watching.