- Can I tell you something I'm bad at?
I am terrible at making clickbait.
Up until two years ago,
my most popular video
was about a basketball
being dropped from a dam
with a bit of backspin.
It takes off like a rocket and shoots out
way further than you'd expect.
This video was embedded
on literally hundreds of news websites.
And in its first week, it
got 16.3 million views,
but almost none of those views
came on the YouTube platform.
Why?
Because I gave it this thumbnail
and I called it "Strange
Applications of the Magnus Effect."
This video is sponsored by KiwiCo.
More about them at the end of the show.
Now, I believe within YouTube,
I'm used as an example of how
not to package your video.
As if to demonstrate just how bad
a title and thumbnail this is,
someone else re-uploaded the
video with the clever title,
"Basketball Dropped From Dam."
And within a few weeks,
that video had received
tens of millions of views on YouTube.
This is when YouTube gave
me access to ContentID.
That's the system that
allows you to earn revenue
when someone else re-uploads
your videos, which was good,
but I still wasn't very good at clickbait.
So for this video, I called in an expert.
I wanted to see your reaction face.
Can you give me like a reaction face?
Like what's a good thumbnail face?
- Oh, I got you.
This is a thumbnail face.
(Derek laughs)
I have like 10, I go through
the motions of like...
(Derek laughs)
And then we just take the best one,
I probably have like
500 of these just saved
and we can just Photoshop
my face on my face.
That way, I don't have to do it anymore.
- When I started on this
platform, some 10 years ago,
clickbait was less important.
Subscribers were what mattered,
because most of the views
came from the sub feed.
And videos went viral usually
by getting a lot of attention elsewhere,
like on Reddit or Facebook,
not due to the YouTube algorithm.
But once you had a big
video and people subscribed,
well, then your next video
would likely get a lot of views
from those subscribers.
So YouTube would take that popular video
and share it with more people.
And so you'd get more subscribers
in a positive feedback loop.
But soon, YouTube realized
that this did not create
the best experience for the viewer.
They discovered that
showing people only videos
from channels they were
subscribed to led to fewer clicks,
less watch time and less engagement
with the site as a whole.
Plus, they knew that
relying on other platforms
to drive traffic to viral hits was risky,
since those other platforms might disable
the traffic at any time.
So they needed to make YouTube
a destination in itself.
They wanted people to come to YouTube,
see videos that interested them,
click on at least one of them
and watch it for a while.
Ideally get sucked down
the YouTube rabbit hole
and spend hours on the site
without even noticing it.
The ultimate resource is people's time
and attention, and every platform
is trying to capture as
much of it as possible.
So, to make YouTube
this go-to destination,
they had decrease the
importance of subscribers,
make it less like a podcast app
where you only get the
shows you're subscribed to,
and more like Reddit,
where stuff with the most
engagement rises to the top.
But that necessarily meant increasing
the importance of clickbait.
Now, there seems to be a paradox
when it comes to clickbait.
People almost universally
claim to hate it,
but you also see it everywhere.
So why is this?
Well, one of the problems
is we don't all agree
on the definition of clickbait.
When I google it, the top definition is,
on the internet, content
whose main purpose
is to attract attention
and encourage visitors
to click on a link to
a particular webpage.
We could call this type I clickbait,
and there doesn't seem to
be anything wrong with it.
I mean, if you didn't
try to attract attention
and get people to click on your links,
then you wouldn't really
be doing your job.
But there is a second definition.
One that I think more people ascribe to,
which is something such
as a headline designed
to make readers want to
click on a hyperlink,
especially when the link leads to content
of dubious value or interest.
Wikipedia says, "A defining
characteristic of clickbait
is that it is sensationalized
or misleading."
And it also talks about teasers
that intentionally withhold information
to exploit the "curiosity gap."
They give you enough
information to make you curious,
but not enough to satisfy that curiosity.
Here are two actual titles
from a news website.
Nine out of 10 Americans
are completely wrong
about this mind blowing fact.
And someone gave some kids some scissors.
Here's what happened next.
I think we can all agree
that these are examples
of bad type II clickbait.
Now, imagine a clickbait
space where on one axis,
you have how misleading
or sensationalized it is.
And on the other, how much information
is intentionally withheld
to create a curiosity gap.
Well, then these two titles
fall in the top right corner.
And these are the zones
of type II clickbait.
At the other extreme,
you have things that are so
unsensationalized as to be dull.
You could call this the dead zone.
Now, here is where you would find
"Strange applications
of the Magnus Effect."
I mean, I didn't tell you
what the applications were.
Now, in the middle is where you
would find type I clickbait.
But honestly, I think type
I and type II clickbait
are so different, that
we shouldn't even use
the same word for them.
Instead of type I clickbait,
my friend and YouTuber, Brady
Heron suggested legitbait.
I mean, it might sound
enticing, but it is legit.
Instead of type II clickbait,
we could use clicktrap,
clicktrick, linktrap or dupechute.
What's important to recognize
is that for any given video,
there is no one true title and thumbnail.
Each video could have
hundreds or thousands
of different legitbait titles.
For example, how does a zero-G plane work?
I went on a plane that does
parabolic trajectories.
What happens to fire on a zero-G plane?
Now, the most enticing
titles and thumbnails
are found close to type II clickbait.
I'm reminded of the infographic
by smarter every day,
showing that on social media,
the greatest engagement
occurs close to the boundary
of what's allowable.
But remember that everyone's
definition of clickbait
is different, and everyone's perceptions
of words and images are different.
So these are not clear boundaries.
They're actually kind of fuzzy.
What for one person might be legitbait,
for someone else, could be a clicktrap.
What's clear is that on a site
where click-through rate is important,
clickbait of all types is inevitable.
How important to a video's success
is the title and thumbnail?
- Very important. Of course.
If they don't click on the video,
they don't watch it.
You can't get 10 million views
unless 10 million people
click on the video.
So, I mean, it's literally that simple.
They don't click on it,
they don't watch it.
- So, why is clickbait everywhere?
Well, because it works.
More enticing thumbnails get more clicks.
Despite some people's claims
that they won't click or they'll unsub,
it's just like evolution.
Whatever survives, multiplies
and traits become amplified.
If you don't begrudge
the giraffe its long neck
so it can reach the highest leaves,
can you begrudge a YouTuber the red arrow
that allows them to
reach further audiences?
I talked about this in
my video two years ago.
To be successful as a YouTuber,
you need to optimize two things,
watch time and the click-through
rate of your videos.
That's the number of times
the title and thumbnail are clicked,
divided by the total number
of times they're shown.
That's the number of impressions.
Now at the time,
this was something of a revelation for me
because I always thought my
job was to make great videos.
And then a title and thumbnail
that adequately represented
what the video was about.
But now I've realized that
making the title and thumbnail
is at least half the job.
This is not just because
better titles and thumbnails
get you more clicks,
but because better titles and thumbnails
will get you way more impressions.
YouTube has limited real estate
with which to show you
virtually infinite content.
And so it's not enough
to make a good video
even if people watch all of it,
you also have to make
a title and thumbnail
that gets clicked,
especially in competition
with other really good
titles and thumbnails.
That's the only way you can expect YouTube
to give you more impressions.
Now, the big development
since my last video on this
is YouTube introduced real-time metrics
like views, impressions
and click-through rate.
Now, I suggested this
would create an arms race.
So what you can bet will happen
is that creators will launch a video
and then they'll be sitting there
with all these different
variants of thumbnails
and they'll be swapping them out
and looking at what that
does to click-through rate
and then going with the one
that leads to the greatest
click-through rate.
And this is basically what has happened.
Let me give you my favorite example.
Last year, I made a video about asteroids,
which I thought was really good.
I called it "Asteroids:
Earth's Biggest Threat,"
which is something Stephen Hawking said.
And people were very
positive about the video.
They thought it was maybe one of my best,
but the performance
was well below average.
In its first day,
asteroids was ranked ninth
out of my previous 10 videos.
It was probably on target
for about one and a half million views.
So I tried different titles and thumbnails
like, "Asteroid Impact:
What Are Our Chances?"
Or "Asteroid Impact: What Could We Do?"
But none of these changes
got much traction.
And then on day three after launch,
我把标题和封面改成了
I changed the title and thumbnail
“这些小行星撞击地球才是我们真正得担心的” 【BV1TK4y1L7x9】
to "These Are the
Asteroids to Worry About."
这则视频立刻就有了起色
And immediately the video
started doing better.
它很快就从我表现最差劲的视频之一
It quickly shot up from almost
my worst performing video
变成了最好的
to my best.
现在它已经有1400万次观看了
It now has 14 million views.
视频本身没有改变
Nothing about the video changed,
仅仅是一张图片和一句话 【的区别】
just that one image and 38 characters.
但是正因如此，这则视频有了
But because of that, the video has reached
接近10倍于其他视频的人气
nearly 10 times as many people
as it otherwise would have.
并且标题和封面准确地描述了
And the title and thumbnail
accurately describe
视频的内容
what the video is about.
当然 这里也卖了个关子
I mean, sure, there's a curiosity gap,
但你没法在标题中
but you couldn't explain the whole concept
解释所有概念
in the length of the title.
所以如果你看到一个YouTuber
更换了标题和封面
So if you see a YouTuber
changing titles and thumbnails,
这就是原因
this is why.
因为这种做法能得到数倍的回报
Because that effort can be
rewarded many times over.
我也见到有人反对这种做法
I've seen people
objecting to this practice
因为他们认为这么做
because they think the creator
是创作者在欺骗观众
is trying to dupe their audience,
让他们重复点击一个视频多次
get them to click on the
same video more than once,
但是事情并非如此
but that's not it.
关键在于让Youtube
The whole point is to get YouTube
向更多的人展示标题和封面
to show the title and
thumbnail to more people.
以此增加严重依赖点击率的
We're trying to increase
the number of impressions,
视频展示次数
which is heavily dependent
on the click-through rate.
最近我的许多视频都有这种典型的观看曲线
Now, a lot of my recent videos
have this typical view curve.
在我发布视频之后有一个初始的尖峰
There's an initial spike
after I release the video
之后是一段低谷 然后是第二个凸包
and then a dip, and then a second bump
在当我找到更好的标题和封面之后
after I have figured out a
better title and thumbnail.
我换掉标题和封面
I change the title and thumbnail
然后观察实时播放量统计
and I watch the real time view graph.
我期待观看量会有明显的增加
What I'm looking for is a
noticeable bump in views.
有时没有改观 有时变得更糟
Sometimes there's no change,
sometimes it gets worse,
但偶尔你也会看到这样的结果
but on occasions, when you
see something like this,
这说明你找到了一个赢家【好标题】
well then, you know you've found a winner.
这是所有大牌YouTuber都在做的事情
This is something all the
big YouTubers are doing.
即使Mr. Beast也没法事先知道
Not even Mr. Beast knows exactly
哪个封面是最好的
which thumbnail will work best beforehand.
- 你是否曾经更换过标题和封面
Have you ever changed
a title and thumbnail
然后视频的表现变好了
and then the video did better?
- 哦 当然
- Oh, of course.
- 我一般制作两三个封面
So everybody, I usually make
like two or three thumbnails,
如果封面没有达到想要的效果
and then if it's not
doing as well as I want,
我通常会换掉标题看看有没有改善
we usually just swap 'em out
and see if it does better.
因为你并不知道【人们会对什么感兴趣】
'cause the thing is like,
you don't really know.
除非你是全能的存在
I mean, you could know if you
just were an almighty being
你只能预计人们会对什么感兴趣
that could just predict what
people would be interested in,
但是 通常
but you know, usually...
比如说 你可以做捉迷藏【的视频】
Like, you can do hide and seek.
你并不知道你藏在树上
You don't really know if
like you hiding in a tree
有人从树下走过是不是个好封面
and then someone walking
below you is a good thumbnail.
或者藏在垃圾箱里 他们从你面前走过 【此处英文字幕似乎有误】
Or if you hiding a trash can and
them walking in front of you.
所以 你该两个都做
So, you know, just do both
然后看哪个更能激起人们的兴趣
and then see which one interests
people a little bit more.
- 我也这么想
- I feel the same way,
但我觉得比起大部分人
but I do feel like you have a better sense
你对此有更好的把握
of this than like most people.
- 当然
- Of course.
我是说 没有别人能一个视频达到4000万播放
I mean, no one gets 40
million views a video.
(大笑)
(both laughing)
- 但是更多播放是为了什么呢
- But what is the point
in getting more views?
如果你觉得人皆利己
If you're cynical,
你可能会说这都是为了名利
you might say it's all
about money and fame.
而其中固然有经济上的动力
And while there are certainly
financial incentives
这并不是我追求更多观看的原因
to getting more views,
that's not why I do it.
作为一个教育向的YouTuber
As an educational YouTuber,
我认为这里有两个重要原因
I think there are two very good reasons
要使用守序的标题党
for using excellent type I clickbait
代替平铺直叙
over more straightforward packaging.
为了理解第一个原因
To understand the first reason,
我们来考虑一下我最近视频
let's consider two
different possible titles
的两个不同标题
for my most recent video.
一个标题是 “这道看似简单的数学题没有人解得出来” 【BV1Ty4y1778o】
I called it "The Simplest Math
Problem No One Can Solve,"
但这视频是有关 Collatz 猜想的
but it's a video about
the Collatz conjecture.
所以也许一个更直接的标题是
So perhaps a more straightforward title
就这么叫它 【Collatz 猜想】
would have been simply to call it that.
问题在于，如果我发布一则
The problem is, if I publish a video
名为 “Collatz 猜想” 的视频
called the Collatz conjecture,
最可能点击它的
the most likely people to click on it
是那些已经知道 Collatz 猜想的人
are those who already know
what the Collatz conjecture is.
而大多数人从未听说过它
And the vast majority of people
will never have heard of it.
所以对他们而言 这个标题是无意义的
So for them, the title is meaningless
只有他们中抱有相当好奇心的
and only the very curious
或者那些超爱 Veritasium 的才会点击
or those who really like
Veritasium would click.
相比之下 把它叫做 “这道看似简单的数学题
In contrast, calling it
"The Simplest Math Problem
没有人解得出来" 向每个人传达了
No One Can Solve,"
conveys more information
有关视频的更多信息
about the video to everyone.
这意味着更多人会点进来
And this means more
people can click on it,
更多从未听说过
most of whom will never have heard
Collatz 猜想的人
of the Collatz conjecture.
这样我才能教他们新知识
So I get to teach them something new.
并且由于视频有更高的点击率
And since the video has a
higher click-through rate,
YouTube 会向更多人展示它
YouTube shows it to even more people.
所以如果我的目标是通过最大化数量来
So if my aim is to increase
the level of knowledge
提升世界的知识水平
in the world by the
maximum amount possible,
这就是我的做法
this is the way to do it.
另一个需要优化标题和封面的原因是
The second reason we need to
optimize titles and thumbnails
为了支持这个频道的主要目标
is to support the major
goal of this channel.
我们正试着就我们解决的每个问题
We are trying to make
the best science films
制作最好的科普影片
on every topic we tackle.
这意味着去拜访摄录实验的专家
That means traveling to meet
experts in film experiments,
请人制作道具
hiring people to build props,
制作壮观的动画效果 研究 和事实核查
make spectacular animations,
research and fact check.
我们聘请专业顾问
We hire expert consultants
来反复核对我们的工作
to double and triple check our work.
我不是想拍vlog
I don't wanna make vlogs.
我想在YouTube上制作科学记录片
I wanna make science
documentaries on YouTube
足以让电视节目【？】相形见绌
that put broadcast to shame.
And to make this possible and sustainable,
the videos have to get
views and lots of them.
And to do that, we have to make
the best titles and thumbnails we can.
YouTuber and Patreon CEO, Jack Conte
has talked about adjusting your packaging.
The idea is know what
you're passionate about,
what you won't compromise on
and that stuff goes in the box.
All the rest, like what
paper it's wrapped in,
that's the packaging.
So the video is my focus
and the title and thumbnail
are the packaging that
I'm happy to adjust,
so I can make the type of
videos that are important to me.
Now, is it ironic that a
channel whose whole purpose
is to promote a true seeking mindset
has to experiment at the
edge of what is truthful
in order to fulfill that purpose?
It is something that I
often worry about.
You know, when I did like
risking my life to do X,
it's like, well, what probability of death
does there have to be for
you to risk your life?
Like 50%?
- I love how he always overthinks things.
(laughs)
That's funny.
He's like, is my life risked enough
where I can put I risked my life?
I only had a 9% chance of dying
and I need at least a 13% chance.
You're so funny.
He was the same way two years ago
when he asked me all this stuff.
I was like, "Dude, just do
whatever makes the most sense.
- Yeah, I mean, obviously
I feel like my instincts
are not good.
But what I realized
is that I don't have
to trust my instincts.
This problem of getting the
best title and thumbnail,
well, it's a scientific problem.
We're just asking which accurate
representation of the video
will get the most clicks
from a general audience.
And that's a problem we can use
the scientific method to solve.
So I've hired a couple
of really bright people
and we spend a lot of time brainstorming
and making titles and
thumbnails and testing them out.
For example, on Twitter and Patreon.
Varitasium titles and
thumbnails have gotten better,
not because I'm better at it,
but because of my team and our testing.
If you have ideas about
how we could do it better,
please get in touch.
The results have often
contradicted what I expected.
I mean, this video seemed
to perform 10% better
when we excluded the word
surprising from the title.
So it became simply The
Secret of Synchronization.
I thought these two titles
were basically a toss up,
but Patreon had a strong
preference for one over the other.
What's interesting about this research
is that the more clickable
titles and thumbnails
often better represent
the content of the video.
Let me give you some examples.
One thing I didn't expect
when YouTube brought in
the real time analytics tools
and allowed title and thumbnail changes
to affect impressions,
was that it would also
work for older videos.
So here is an old video
that I originally entitled,
"Why the Neutron is the
Hero of Nuclear Physics."
In hindsight, it's a weird,
kinda meaningless title.
So I changed it to, "Why Einstein Thought
Nuclear Weapons Impossible."
It's clearer, more accurate.
And this is what happened
to views after the change.
I changed "Strange Applications
of the Magnus Effect"
to "Backspin Basketball Flies Off Dam."
Again, more accurate.
And the video is now
being watched on YouTube.
Probably 10 million more views
than it otherwise would have had.
Even anti-clickbait has proven effective.
Here's a video I originally titled,
"Are Negative Ions Good For You?"
Which is a question nobody asked ever.
Now, I changed it to,
"Do Salt Lamps Work?"
Seriously.
And here's the result:
One and a half million more views.
I think looking at these examples,
you could easily make the case
that YouTube has made
me better at what I do.
It has improved the clarity and accuracy
of my titles and thumbnails.
It's helped me figure out
what is interesting to my audience
and how to encapsulate
that in a single image
and fewer than 50 characters.
For those of you who worry that a focus
on titles and thumbnails will prevent me
from picking challenging science topics,
well, I simply ask you
to look at the videos
from the last year or two,
like the ones on Gödel's
incompleteness theorem,
general relativity, Penrose tilings,
the logistic map, Newton's
method of calculating Pi,
the one way speed of light.
Good titles and thumbnails
make it possible
to tackle these topics
and to reach more people
who have heard of them before.
There is a symbiotic relationship
between views and video quality.
The more views we get, the more people,
locations, props and equipment
and research we can invest in.
This makes the next video
better than the last.
If we can be good at
titles and thumbnails,
the ultimate outcome is better videos.
That is something I think
you and I both want.
Hey, this video is sponsored by KiwiCo,
a long time supporter of the channel.
Now KiwiCo makes awesome
hands on projects for kids,
including big kids like me.
They have eight subscription lines
targeted at different age groups,
all the way down to newborns.
What I love about KiwiCo crates
is that they make learning fun
and something to look forward to.
I mean, when I pull out a crate,
my kids just jump at the
chance to make it with me.
And all the materials you
need come right in the box.
So there's no need to run to the store.
You just open it up and go.
My kids and I just built
this domino machine,
which, who knows, might be
inspiration for a viral video.
Now, the big idea is that
while playing and having fun,
kids learn about STEAM concepts.
That is science, technology,
engineering, art and math.
And in addition to the project,
there's a magazine with a lot
of additional information.
So I think this is the best way to learn.
By doing something
yourself and having fun,
it's how education should be.
So if you wanna try it out,
go to Kiwico.com/veritasium50,
and you'll get 50% off your
first month of any crate.
I will put that link
down in the description.
So I wanna thank KiwiCo
for sponsoring Veritasium,
and I wanna thank you for watching.